Okay. Last time we started on the issue of
resource management using it as an example,
designing a string class,
pretending we didn't already
have such a class
available in the standard
C plus plus library.
We decided that a string object will hold
a pointer to a dynamically allocated array.
We wrote a constructor that allocates
C array when a string is created,
and we realized that we needed to
write a destructor to ensure that
that array is deallocated
when the string object goes away.
If we didn't do that,
we'd have a memory leak.
Now, you might think, Okay, that was easy,
grab storage at creation,
give it back when the string
goes away. We're done, right?
If so, you'd be very wrong.
So let me pose a new problem now and
see where we fall flat
on our faces with the
string type as we defined it.
What we've written is correct
so far but not complete.
So here's the new situation I want to set up.
We have this function H. H creates a string,
initializes it with hello.
It calls the function F,
passing it the string S,
F receives the string
and then does its thing.
So let's see what is happening.
So you've got this constructor code
here and the destructor there.
So remember, the destructor is basically
setting up constructor is
setting up the string,
dynamically allocating the array
of characters, putting the text in there.
The destructor is deleting the storage.
And so let's see what happens here.
So let me go to the board on this again.
All right. So if we enter the function H,
H creates a string
S. We know what that's going to do.
The string length is five.
We'll get a pointer to
the dynamic storage before
the hilo. Right there.
Now we're going to call the function F
passing at S. Now,
look at the declaration of F.
F's argument T is a type string.
Not pointed to string,
not reference to string, but string.
So what are we doing here?
We're not passing by reference.
We're passing by value.
Passing by value means copying.
It means that T will be a copy of
S. If you pass
something to a function by value,
the original object is copied
into the parameter for the function,
and then the function
can do whatever it wants with
that parameter has no effect on the original.
That's what passing by value should be.
Alright, so that means
that here we are in the environment of H.
We have this thing
S. We're going to be entering
the environment of T. I'm sorry, of F,
and F has its own local variable
T. It's a brand new object,
and it's going to be constructed as a copy of
S. So how's that going to work?
Well, we didn't say how strings get copied.
So the compiler says,
If you don't tell me how to copy a type,
I will just simply copy each member.
So the compiler says,
You didn't tell me how to copy strings.
So to initialize T as a copy of S,
I will just copy
this pointer and copy this integer.
Okay, so the pointer and the integer
get copied, and T looks like that.
So now,
from the point of view of the function,
Ts, it's got the text, hello.
It's a five character string.
Looks good. If the function
does things like, Hey,
I want to take a look
at the third character in the string,
maybe you have
some member function to let you
look at particular characters in the string.
I'll find the right character.
Okay looks great. But look
at the weird things that could happen.
If the function does something
to modify the string,
for example, let's say there's
a member function of string that
lets you modify some
of the characters in the string.
Maybe the function F decides
to change the character,
the beginning of the string from an H to a J.
So hello becomes jello, right?
It's taking T, it's saying,
I'm going to modify the character
beginning to a J, so it does.
Well, that's a little weird, right?
Cause that means the string
S, the original object,
now the text is different than it was before,
but I thought passing by value means,
the original object is
not going to get modified,
and yet it has been.
So that's a little weird,
but that's not the real problem.
The real problem comes
when we leave the function F,
when we return from the function F,
any local variables of F go away.
T, the parameter T is a local variable of F.
So this string is going to go away.
Now, when a string goes away,
the destructor is called.
So the destructor is called on T.
The destructor is told
to delete the array this points to.
So it goes away. And now
that the destructors done his job,
these are both built in types,
nothing else happens, so T's gone.
And so we return to the function,
and S has been radically changed.
Here, we thought that passing by
value means
our original object won't get modified.
In fact, S is now in a horrible state.
The array's gone. S has a dangling pointer.
It's got a pointer to storage that
no longer belongs to your program.
So any attempt to follow
that pointer in the rest
of this code is undefined behavior.
Now, maybe the rest of the code
doesn't ever try to follow that plan.
Maybe the only thing we do with
F with S after this point is maybe say,
Hey, S, how long is the string?
And maybe our member function
of string that tells you how long
the string is simply looks at
this number and gives it
back to you and says,
Oh, it's five characters. Okay, thank you.
But we're going to run
into trouble at some point.
When we leave the function,
when we leave the function H,
the string is going to
go S is going to go away,
so the destructor is called,
and the destructors going to
call delete on a pointer
to storage that's already been deleted.
That's always undefined behavior.
If you call delete with a pointer to
storage that no longer
belongs to your program,
it's been given back to the operating system,
that's undefined behavior,
and on most systems will cause a crash.
So we're totally messed up here.
So again, the problem was
that letting the compiler say how strings
get copied is going to turn into simply copy
the members and the essence
of the problem is T
and S are sharing the same array,
and that's where the problem lies.
Any changes through T to
the array is going to be reflected in S. But,
the real problem is going to
be when T goes away,
the array that's shared
by both of them goes away.
And so now S has a dangling pointer,
and even if we don't come
into run into trouble earlier,
by the time the instructors called,
we're going to be in bad shape.
So that's the source of
the problem that T is
sharing the same array from S.
Now, when I think of copying, uh you know,
if I pass a copy of
an integer parameter of
a function, that'll be an integer.
Then this gets copied here.
This is entirely independent
of this guy. There's nothing shared here.
The copy of this integer is
totally distinct from this integer here.
That's what I want copying to do.
I want the newly created object as
a copy of the original to
be totally independent of the original.
So that means T should
probably have its own array of characters,
not share it with S, get
its own array of character.
So to make that happen,
we have to tell the compiler,
I don't want you to
say how to copy something.
I'm going to tell you how to copy.
So to do that, we have to declare
an appropriate way of
creating a string from another string.
Well,
creating a string, that's a constructor.
So let me provide a constructor for
string that takes as
its argument, another string.
I'll pass it by constant reference.
So I'm
creating another constructor for string.
It says, how to create
a string from another string.
And I'm passing it by constant reference for
reasons that I'll get to later. So let's see.
How do I create a string?
How do I create a string from
another string? Well, let's see.
So I've got to make sure that
I am properly initialized.
So that means my LN
and my text have to be properly set.
So my MLN well,
that'll just be the other guy's MLN.
Okay, so if the other guys a
five character string with the text hello,
then I'll set my length to five.
Now, my text should
not just be a pointer
to the other guy's storage.
I need my own array of characters.
So I will allocate
my own array of
characters of the right length.
So now I have a dynamically allocated array
of the right number of characters,
but they're uninitialized.
So let's copy
the other guy's text into my text.
Let's copy the C string from
the other guy into me. And there we have it.
There is a correct
implementation of the constructor for
a string that takes
a string another string as its argument.
And I know there's
going to be people raising objections.
I haven't seen if they already
have raising some objections.
Will this even compile? Yes, it will compile.
I'll explain why. But let's
see what it does to
see how it solves the problem.
So remember that code,
and let me go back to the picture.
So now we're saying,
Okay, let's do the following.
As is going to be copied into.
So the compiler says,
Oh, okay, we got to copy a string.
Did you tell me how to do that?
Did you tell me how to create
a string from another string?
And we did. We have a constructor
that says how to construct
a string from another string.
Qu says, Oh, okay.
Then instead of following what I would do,
which is copy the data members,
I'll do what you tell me.
So what I told you to do was to
take now now in the copy constructor,
that's what that constructors called.
In the constructor, it says,
how to copy one string, how
to create a string from another string,
the object being constructed
is the one that this pointer points to.
Remember,
every member function has a this pointer
that points to the
object the function is called on.
So in this case, T is
the one that's being constructed,
so that this pointer is pointing to
T. And the parameter,
the thing we're copying from
other let's go to be
F. So other is a reference to a strain.
So other will be another name for S.
So copy in
the constructor that I just written,
that copy constructor,
S plays the role of other.
So what did we say to do? We said,
set my own length to
the other guy's length. Okay.
Then I said, dynamically
allocate an array of N plus one characters.
So five plus one is six,
dynamically allocate an array of
six characters and store
a position store the pointer into my text.
Okay. Then the last thing I said was
string copy into my text
the other guy's text.
And that'll copy the characters
up to and including Zerobte.
And so when that constructor finishes,
when that constructor finishes,
here's T. It looks like a copy of S,
and in fact, it's totally
independent of S now.
So whatever we do to T has
no effect on S. Perfect.
That's exactly what copying should do.
So now the function
can do whatever it wants to T.
If it wants to call some
member function of string
that'll let us change into a J, that's fine.
Has no effect on S. Eventually,
when we leave the function F,
T will be destroyed.
The destructor will be called on
T. The destructor will
get rid of that storage.
So the body of the destructor for strength,
gets rid of that storage, and
then step two of destruction.
Well, these are built in
types, so nothing happens.
And so then T can go away safely.
And we're back here, and
S is in perfectly good shape,
unchanged, exactly what we want.
So we have solved the problem of,
you know, the undefined behavior that
will happen if we don't
properly copy the string.
So let me go back and look at
some terminology and address
some of the issues
that people
are some people are no doubt thinking.
So first of all, terminology,
this constructor is
called the copy constructor.
So this is the copy constructor.
The copy constructor is
called whenever a string
is being created from another string.
So there's a a number
of contexts where that happens.
So if I create a string, X from S,
there is creating
a string from another string.
That would call the copy constructor.
Here's another way to create
a string from another string.
I'm creating a string X,
and it's a copy
of it's going to come from that string
S. Also, passing by value.
In this case, if we pass
a string by value to a function,
that will call the copying instructor.
So that's built into the language.
The language recognizes passing by value.
If your parameter is
a string, not a pointer to a string,
not a reference to a string, if
your parameter is a string
and you're passing a string,
call the copy constructor.
Also, if you're returning
a value from a function,
a value, not a pointer or a reference.
So in other words, I I I have
some function blah if
I have some function blah
that declares a local variable
for some string and builds
up some answer in there and
ultimately decides to
return the value of that string.
So notice blah is returning a string,
not a pointer to a string,
not a reference to a string, but a string.
That means the expression here is value
will be copied back
to the caller of the function.
So whoever calls the function blah gets
a copy of the
final value of this local variable.
How is that copied from the function
back to the caller
through the copy constructor?
So those are the circumstances
where the copy constructor gets called.
And whenever you have
an object that has
some resource that it holds,
you got to think
about the copying behavior there.
You got to think, What do I want to
do if one of these things gets copied?
What do I do about the resource?
Do I have both objects
share the same resource?
That usually leads to problems.
So, you know,
maybe somehow figuring out
making a copy of the resource.
Or if it doesn't make sense
to make a copy of the resource,
then maybe preventing copying entirely,
which is something we're
not going to do right now.
We'll see how to do that later.
Okay.
Another question
that often comes up at this point.
I haven't been looking
at the questions right now,
but I'm sure it's been asked already is,
you know, why am I passing this by reference?
Could I also pass it by value?
Well, let's see the variations.
We could, if we want, declare
the copy constructor this way.
It's pretty rare, but you can do this
where I'm creating
a string from another string,
but the copy constructor itself is
allowed to modify the string
that's being copied from.
Well, it's kind of weird
because usually when you think
about making copies of
something, you say, Well,
the process of making a copy of
something should not modify the original,
and that's why it's usually
passed by constant reference.
But here's a circumstance where it might be.
Suppose that string for
some performance monitoring reasons or
something is keeping track
of the number of copies made from the string.
So maybe we have some kind of
variable member function data member
that's going to be the number of
copies that have been made from me.
So when I'm first created,
we'll initialize that to zero, let's say.
And then anytime the string is copied.
The copy constructor, in addition to
copying what it's doing
with the mtext, et cetera,
is also adding one to the number of copies
made from the object being copied from.
So it is modifying
the original object by saying,
Hey, one more copy of you has
been made. Record that for yourself.
That's okay. It's uncommon, but it's okay.
Usually, it's one of these things
where notice that doesn't really
conceptually modify
the strings value in any significant way.
The original guy still has
the same text and the same length.
It's just another little bit
of information about it that,
you know, we might want to keep track of.
So this is okay,
rather uncommon, but okay.
What definitely is not legal,
and I'll show you why is what
if we have the copy constructor
take its argument pass by value?
That is, we decide,
here's how you create a string
from another string,
and my copy instructor here or
my supposed copy constructor
here is going to take
us argument passed by
value, something like that.
Well, this is illegal
because it doesn't make sense.
And let me show you why. So suppose
that were my copy constructor.
Then here's what happens. We got S created.
We're calling the function
F. S is being passed
by value to create
T. So this brand new object T
is going to be created as a copy of S.
So to
create this brand new object
T as a copy of S,
we got to call the copy constructor.
Now, in the copy constructor,
the object being created is T,
so that this pointer points to T.
And the parameter
that is going to come from S,
the parameter is other passed by value.
So it's a brand new string.
So there's going to be
this brand new string called O
That's going to be
initialized as a copy of S.
Well, how is other going
to be initialized as a copy of
S by calling the copy constructor?
So in order to get S
passed to other so that then we can create T,
we've got to call the copy constructor,
which will say, Okay,
this pointer will point to other,
and S is going to be
passed to the parameter to
that call to the copy constructor,
which is passed by value,
which is a second instance of other,
which has to be initialized from
S. Once we have done that,
then we can go to
the copy constructor in order
to copy that into here,
and once that's done, we can go
to the copying instructor and finish
the copying instructive body to copy it into
T. So you see where this is going.
The copy constructor defines
what it means to pass by value.
How do you pass by value?
You make a copy by
calling the copy constructor.
So if the copy constructor
itself took its argument pass by value,
you've got this infinite circular definition.
Well, how do we get the argument to it by
calling the copy constructor? Oh, okay.
Well, how do we get the argument to
that copy constructors argument
by calling the copy constructor?
It makes no sense. So for
that reason, no, no, no, no, no.
The other parameter is passed by reference.
It's not going to be a brand new string
as a copy of the original.
It's another name for the original.
So is another name for S,
and that's why we don't go crazy here.
So let me put this back here.
We'll pass it by reference,
and in fact, of course,
it'll be constant reference
because we don't modify the original object.
So let's make that promise.
So now we're good. Back to
being a legal copy instructor.
Okay. Now, the other question
that people ask is,
well, wait a minute.
I'm talking about Men of O and
text of other Not Mamnin Mam text,
but the private members of the other string.
Is that allowed?
The answer is yes.
You might say, Well, wait a minute.
I thought that if
a member is declared private,
then the only place you can talk about them
are in the member functions
of the class they belong to.
I'll say, Yes,
that's exactly what's happening here.
You say, but I
thought you could only talk about
the private members of
the object that this pointer points to.
No, I never said that. I've never in 31,
never prior in 32.
That is, you know, talking about
MLN by itself is just shorthand for
saying this arrow LN and this arrow text.
So you know that
for the object you
called the member function on,
of course, you could talk about the
private members for that object.
But you can actually also
talk about the private members
of this one means Emlen.
You can also talk about
the private members of any string.
So it's not just the string
that this pointer points to,
but a member function
of string can talk about
the private members of any string.
Why is that?
Well, that wasn't Strostrp's original idea.
He thought the idea should be
that if I call
a member function on this object,
the member function can deal with
the private members only of this object,
not of other objects, not
even other objects of the same type.
That's what he originally planned to do.
And then he realized
the need for writing copy constructors,
and then he realized that,
oh, that can make
copy constructors very hard to write.
If I can't get at
the internals of the other guy,
then it might be hard
or even impossible for me
to write a copy constructor.
Now, depending on how
the string type is declared,
it may or may not be possible
to make a copy
from it using the public interface.
For example, if string has
a public function to
give you the length of the string,
you wouldn't need to talk about the
M Ln member or the other guy.
This could be a little harder.
How do you do a string copy from
the other If string does not have
a member function to give you back a pointer
to its own internal
representation, the character array,
then that could be a problem, but,
you know, maybe I could get
around that problem by I don't know,
maybe I could manually
write a loop that would I don't know,
my text is the other guys maybe I have
a member function called
give me the character at this position.
If that's a public function,
and then I got to make sure
my text with the zero byte there.
If there were public functions for the length
and how to get the value
of a character at
a certain position of the string,
then yeah, I could implement
the copying instructor using
only the public interface of the other guy.
The thing is, in this case, I could do it,
but look, it's more work for me
and maybe not as efficient.
Maybe the library string copy function
is optimized to do
all kinds of clever things very efficiently.
Maybe character at is
implemented to always check
the subscript for validity.
So if I write this myself,
I am paying the cost of
checking that K is always a valid subscript,
even though from the structure of
my loop, of course, it is.
So my implementation might
not be as efficient if I
have to go through the public interface.
And maybe there are
some data members that don't have
a direct public way
of accessing their values.
So, in general, he said, you know,
it's much easier to say, now,
now we will allow
a member function of a class to
access private members of
any other object of that type,
not just the one that this pointer points to.
I'll get rid of these redundant
this arrows that I don't need.
And so that's why, that's
why the copy constructor for
string can actually access and can
talk about and access the private members
of other string objects.
So let me write that. Okay.
So it looks like we're out of the woods.
We had a little issue
we hadn't thought about before,
and we fixed that.
So now our resource management
for string is perfect.
Everything's great. No, we
have yet another problem
that has a bunch of complications.
We're handling copying, creating
a brand new string as
a copy of an existing string.
What we have not handled is assignment,
taking an already existing string,
not a newly constructed string,
a string that we're constructing
an already existing string and
giving it a new value,
giving it a different value.
That's different
from creating a brand new string.
The main way it's different is
the starting conditions are different.
When you create a brand new string as
a when you create a brand new string,
you create a brand new string
as a copy of another string,
this storage has nothing in it.
You can do whatever
you want with the storage.
There's nothing in it, so we
can make our copy just fine.
If you're assigning to
this string this already created
already existing string from
another string, that's different.
This guys not starting out
with uninitialized storage.
This guy has, you know, a pointer dynamic
storage and already has a value.
And you can't just assume,
Oh, I can just put whatever I want in it.
Well, what about the old stuff it has?
Yeah. It's a different problem.
So assignment is different from copying.
The end result is kind of the same in that,
hey,
this object looks like a copy of that one.
The starting conditions are different.
And to take care of assignment properly,
we need to learn something new.
The copy constructor only takes care of
creating brand new objects
as a copy of another one.
Assigning is a different story,
but we'll have to take a look at that later.
Um Okay,
there is a misconception
that some people have.
This is clearly assignment.
I mean, that's clearly assignment.
We're not creating a brand new object.
We're taking an already existing object
and assigning something to it.
That's assignment. This is
clearly instruction.
We're creating a brand new object X
that did not exist before and
copying it from S. But then there's
the question of this holdover syntax from C.
So, this syntax for
C in a declaration is allowed.
And what's going on here?
And the answer is
It's copy construction. It's not assignment.
And you say, but there's an equals sign here.
That's not the assignment operator.
This is construction because
we are creating a brand new.
We're creating a brand new object
that did not exist before.
Why did not exist before.
We're declaring Y is a brand new string.
We're giving its very first value
copied from S. It's
not that Y is an existing object that
we are now giving a new value
to, it's getting creative.
That's construction. So be careful.
The meaning of this symbol
here and this symbol here are different.
That's the assignment operator.
This is just a little bit of syntax
that separates the variable you're
declaring from the initialization expression.
So we've seen how to deal with this stuff.
We've written the copy constructor.
We haven't done the assignment operator yet.
So let's say now here, Uh oh.
I spilled coffee on my shirt again.
Give me a second to change.
Okay, where was I?
Let's say now here in the function H,
let's say we have a string,
say initialized to WOW.
And then later on, we assign S to U.
Okay, so you look at it and say,
well, all right,
the goal of assignment
is to make the left hand side
look like a copy of
the right hand side, right?
That's certainly true for integers.
I I I have an integer K and an integer N,
and I say K equals N,
the goal is to take the value of N,
store it in K,
so K looks like a copy of M.
That's what everybody expects
the assignment operator to do.
So it's your job as a class designer to make
sure that assignment works
properly for your class and has that effect?
Well, again, we have a problem here.
If we don't declare
an assignment operator and
implement an assignment operator,
we don't declare an assignment operator,
the compiler writes one for us that
simply assigns each data member.
And that's not going to be right here.
Now you might say, Well, wait a minute
I thought we defined a copy constructor.
The copy constructor only
applies when you are
creating only comes into effect when you're
creating a brand new object
that didn't exist before,
you're constructing a new object,
giving it its very first value.
That's what happens when T gets
created as a copy of S when we call FS.
T didn't exist before we made this call,
and so now we're making the call
and T is getting created for
the very first time is being
created for S. That's
going to be construction.
T will be constructed
by the copying instructor.
But assignment is different.
U is not being
created in this statement. U already exists.
The previous statement created.
So assignments different because
the starting condition is different.
The end result is, yeah,
yeah, U is going to look like a copy of S,
just like T looked like a copy
of S when we use the copying instructor,
passing over to T. But
the starting condition is different.
T did not exist before.
Whatever was in the data member was
uninitialized garbage before
the constructor started executing.
But with the assignment operator,
you already has a value,
and there's already stuff inside you.
It's already been initialized
through a constructor at
sometime in the past,
and now we're giving it a new value.
And that situation is very different.
So let me go to the board again.
This time I'll do it, right? Let me
go to the board again
and see what the story is here.
So we created you
by calling the constructor
that took the C string WOW.
So the length of that is three.
It allocated an array of
four items and started pointering there,
and then copied the text WOW into there.
So after creating you,
the situation looks like that.
So now what we're going to do is
assign, we said,
U gets S. Now,
we didn't say anything
about how to do assignment.
We only said how to do copying,
and assignment is not the same as
copying because the
starting condition is different.
So if we don't say how to do assignment,
the compiler says, Okay,
I will simply assign each data member.
So it assigns the pointer.
So the pointer and tex data member
of U gets assigned from the
tex data member of
S. So that pointer gets assigned over here,
and the five gets assigned over here.
So now you has the text
hello and the length five well,
that looks like a copy of S. Well,
but no, look at the whole picture.
No, it's not a copy of S.
It's sharing the same text as S,
same problem we had with copy constructor.
And so we're certainly going to have
the same problem later on.
W U gets destroyed,
the destructor will get rid of this storage.
And so when S gets destroyed,
we try to call the delete
on already deleted storage.
So it's got
that same problem as copy constructor,
all those same problems, plus
one more a memory leak.
We never got rid of the WOW.
So the old value of you is linked here.
That's what makes assignment
different from copying.
The starting condition is different.
You already had a pointer to dynamic storage,
and so if you were to
even if you applied
the copy constructor to somehow say,
Well, you know, let's
first bring over the length,
then let's allocate new storage
for you to point to.
Even if you were pointing to new storage,
we wiped out the old storage.
So if the assignment operator
simply called the copy constructor,
which it does not, but if it
did, we'd still have a problem.
So we cannot let the compiler
write the assignment operator
for us in this case.
Now, why didn't we have this problem before?
Well, look at the
kinds of things we had before.
We had, for example, a circle object,
and a circle had a radius, I'm sorry,
had an X and Y coordinate in
the center and a radius.
And if I had another circle
that already had a value,
so here's another circle
that already has a value.
If I assign this circle to this circle, now,
we'd never declared an
assignment operator for circle,
so the compiler simply
did member by member assignment.
It assigned the negative two over
to here, the five over to here,
the ten over to here, and
now this circle has negative two,
five and ten. That's fine.
That works. No memory leak, no problem here.
So member my member assignment
works in the case of,
all you have is simple types
that don't hold any resources.
So if you just wipe out the old value by
assigning over the new value, not a problem.
Okay, but now we face something different.
So how do we solve the problem?
So the way Str Stip decided to
do it was say, All right,
assignment will
be a member function of a class.
And if you don't write one,
the compiler writes one for you,
that does member by member assignment.
But if you want to change it, you've
got to write your own
version of the assignment operator.
What that means is the assignment U equals S
is really just a convenient shorthand like
any other operator
defined as a member function.
It's really just a shorthand for take
you call some member function
with S as an argument.
And the name of that member function
is operator equal.
It's a funny looking name
for a function, but again,
this is what happens when you overload
functions of C plus plus.
You do so by creating functions whose name is
the word operator followed
by
the operator symbol that you're overloading.
So assigning STU is
done by calling a member function on you
named operator equals with the argument S.
It's just that we're allowed to
simplify that and write it this way.
So our goal is to write
this operator equal function.
So that we get the correct behavior.
Okay, so let's see
what that function would have to do.
So we start with a condition
where points has some old value,
say it points to
WOW and it has a length of three.
Let me get this out of the way. Now, in
this called operator equal,
so let me write it up here.
Is the object being modified,
so is the object that this pointer points to.
And S will be the other guy.
We'll pass S by
reference to this member function.
We'll show that in a minute.
Okay, so let's see what would have to happen.
Now, we know the goal
is to make you look like a copy of S.
So what are we doing
the copy constructor to make
you look like a copy of S?
Well, we have signed over the length.
So if we change the three to a five,
that's making progress.
That seems reasonable.
Then we dynamically allocated
an array and stored the pointer in here.
Oh, but wait, we've got the old one here.
So we better delete
the storage that you points to.
So somewhere in here before we
replace the pointer here with
a pointer to the new storage,
we need to call Delete on
this pointer to get rid of that storage.
So if we do that, we call
Delete on this pointer,
get rid of that storage.
Now the WOW is gone.
We're not going to have a memory leak
anymore if we do
everything right from here on.
So now we can dynamically allocate
a new array and set you to point to it.
Copy over the text. And when
we're done, we're in great shape.
You looks like a copy of S,
which is what assignment ought to do.
We properly cleaned up the old value of you.
There's no memory leak. And you has
a nice independent copy of S.
So does whatever we do to you,
has no effect on S. Perfect.
That's what we want to have happen.
So the traditional way of
writing the assignment operator
essentially does those steps.
I say traditional because I'll show
you the modern way later.
So the traditional way
Is going to look like this. So almost,
I'm not quite there yet,
but we're getting there.
So we'll have the right hand side,
RHS, or the right hand side of
the operator, the assignment operator.
It's not quite I
mean, it's technically legal,
but it's not quite the conventional way
you write an assignment operator.
I will fix it later, but it's
not quite following the conventions.
I will get to that later.
But the basic idea is
the argument to the assignment operator
will be passed by constant reference.
And so let me write it.
I'll put it here so the code
will be nearby. Okay.
Again, I will fix the signature
to the function later.
So Okay. It's not
quite following the convention.
So we want to clean up the left hand side.
In a call to the operator equal,
that means you gets S means
you were calling the operator
equal member function on S,
which means so this pointer points to U,
and the parameter RHS is a reference to
S. So the this pointer
points to the left hand side object,
the one that we're assigning to,
and RHS is another name for the parameter.
That's the argument we passed.
So we want to delete
the old text of the left hand side.
And now that we've done that, basically,
we would just make
the left hand side look like a copy of
the right hand side by doing
the same thing we did to the right hand side.
But let me note that
this implementation is not quite right.
We'll fix it later,
but I want to make sure I put that
there for people who,
you know, look at this slide.
Look at this text at
some point in the future
and think that this code is correct.
So as long as these labels are here,
this is not correct.
Whoops, pretend the two occurrences of
the word other are really RHS.
It's going to take another 13 minutes
before the guy in the video recognizes that.
So this was the code that I
essentially executed on the board.
I got rid of the WOW
that you used to point to.
And once I did that, I was
free to go ahead and assign
the length and assign something
new to the text to the left hand side.
No problem. Okay.
So now let me
go through and fix up a few things.
Well, first of all, there's something
that's not required for us to do,
but is a convention,
and that is to make o the assignment operator
usable in a similar way
to the way it is for built in types.
So for built in types, like say integers,
if I have an integer K that has the value
three and I have
some integer M that has the value five,
and let's say I have some integer M,
Now, for built in types,
assignment returns a value.
We normally don't use it that way, right?
Normally, we might say something
like after doing this,
K gets N. So that assigns N to K,
replacing the value of K
that was three with
the value of N, which is five.
So this makes K have the value five.
And as it turns out,
this expression returns a value
as well, the new value K.
But we don't use it, right?
We're not using that value as
part of a bigger expression
in most uses the way we write assignment.
But you can if you want.
So for example, if I say M K gets N.
Now, the associativity
of the assignment operator,
unlike every other operator
for the most part,
is right to left, not left to right.
So I didn't write
any parentheses here because I don't have to,
but if I wanted
to be clear about what was happening,
I would put the parentheses here.
In other words, N
is going to be assigned to K,
and then the result of this
expression will be assigned
to M. So the five in N gets assigned to K,
so K will have the value five,
and the result of the assignment
is the new value of
K. N gets assigned
to K and the result
of the expression is five,
the new value of K, and the new value of
K will then also get
assigned to M. So in other words,
the five in N got
assigned to K which got assigned to M.
So you can string together
assignments this way or use
assignments in other contexts
where it'll return a value,
which will be the new value
of the left hand side.
That's not a feature
that's used tremendously much,
but it is part
of the language in C and C plus plus.
So the style for
writing assignment operator for
your own types is to follow the same idea.
Do the same thing, make it so that
your assignment of strings
could be strung together this way.
That is, if I had three strings,
let's have some other string.
So, let's say, these were all strings.
We want the same effect.
So the language says
the precedence of the assignment operator
is right to left,
so this will be treated this way.
So in other words, the goal is
to assign S to U and
then use the result
of the assignment and assign it to.
So what should the result
of the assignment be?
Well, following the pattern
with integers or other built in types,
I guess, the new value of U. So that's it.
The convention in C plus
plus is when you
overload the assignment operator,
you declare it as a function that will
return the new value of the left hand side.
So if the new value of U gets returned,
and that gets assigned to V, well,
then this has the same
effect as it does for integers.
The current value of S, which is
let's say hello gets assigned to U,
and that hello then gets assigned over to V.
Okay, so it's the convention you ought
to follow because everybody does it that way.
So let me see what that looks like in code.
So that would say, apparently,
the assignment operator is going to
return the new value
of the left hand side, which is a string.
So I'll say string for now.
That's not quite again,
it's not quite conventional,
so I'll fix this in a minute.
And this is still not quite
conventional. I'll fix that in a minute.
But the idea would be when we're all done,
we're going to return the new value
of the left hand side.
Now, when we do this assignment,
the left hand side
is you. So this points to you.
So do we say return this no,
we don't say return this.
This is of type pointer to string.
So if we said return this,
we would be returning
a pointer to the left hand side.
That's not what we want to return.
We want to return the
actual new value of the left hand side.
So we have to follow the pointer.
We want to return the
object that this points to.
Star this means the object
that this points to.
Star of any pointer means
the object the pointer points to.
So that's now correct.
We want to return the object
this pointer points to.
Okay, that would work.
It's a bit inefficient,
and it will always be a bit
inefficient for almost any type
you do this for.
So let's see where the inefficiency is.
The problem is, we're returning a value.
We're returning a brand new string,
a copy of star this.
So when a function returns a value,
it's going to return
a temporary object that's
a copy of your return expression.
So return star this is going to say,
Okay, take the left hand side,
which in our case is U and
make a copy of it to return to
the caller so that in an expression
like V gets the result of U gets S,
we assign S over to U,
and then we would be returning
a copy of the new value of U,
a copy of you as
the argument to the
assignment operator for V. In other words,
this thing means take V,
call the operator equal function on U gets S,
but gets S means,
call the operator equal function on
S. Assigning S to U
and then assigning the result to V
is really just two function calls.
Call the member function operator equal on U,
passing it S and
then call the operator equal function on V,
passing it the result of this first call.
So if the results of this first call is
a copy of the new value of you.
It's a copy of you,
then that's going to be used.
The copy of is going to be
used as the argument
to V's assignment operator.
And basically, what we did was we
took the already existing object, right?
The already existing object
that this pointer pointed
to and made a copy of
it for V to assign from.
Well, why not just let V
assign from directly?
Well, how do we do that?
How do we make this function,
not return a copy of
you but you itself, another name for you.
Oh, another name for you.
That's what a reference is.
So the convention is you have
the assignment operator return
a reference to and
now that's the conventional way to write it.
You have the assignment operator return
a reference to the left hand side object.
So returning Star this says,
return the object to this pointer
we're not going to return a copy of it.
We're going to return another name for it.
We're going to return a reference to it.
We don't make a copy of it.
We'll just return another name for it,
which will be immediately then passed
over to the assignment operator here,
which will have RHS
be another name for this other name for you.
It's another name for you.
So no copy of you is being made.
A reference to you is being passed from
the assignment operator back to the caller,
which is then immediately being passed
over to the second call
of operator equal over here.
Again,
don't worry so much about the detail there.
Just remember the convention is
the assignment operator returns
a reference to the
kind of thing you're assigning to,
and the assignment
operators the last statement
the assignment operator should execute should
be a return of star this,
a return on the left hand side.
Okay, so that we
think is something that works.
I'm still leaving up the not quite
right because it's still not quite right.
But it looks like it works.
It cleans up the left hand side,
and then makes the left hand side
look like a copy of the right hand side.
And then by convention, return star this.
So what's wrong there?
Isn't that what should happen?
Well, let's see.
What that code does in
the context of the call of Gs S,
this pointer points to U
and RHS is another name for
S. So it deletes
the mtext of the left hand side object,
then it brings over the length,
then it dynamically allocates
a new array at the right
of this length plus one
and stores a pointer in here,
so the old values gone here,
and then it copies the text.
And then it returns a reference to you.
Okay, that's correct behavior in this case.
Here's the problem. Let's say
we have an array of strings.
So here's some string array,
and there's a bunch of strings in this array.
Each one of these is a string object,
and I have
some algorithm that's going through
this array and rearranging
things and doing all kinds
of stuff with things.
And so in this algorithm,
we're looping around for
various values of I and J.
And so if I is this element,
if I is indicating this element
and J's indicating that element,
then this element is going to
be assigned over to this one.
And so strings get
assigned around from
one array element to another.
Now, every so often in this algorithm,
I and J happen to have the same value.
So we're assigning a string to itself.
Now, what do you expect
happens when you assign an object to itself?
Well, again, you know,
think about plain old types like integers.
So I have an integer K with a value three,
and if I were to ever say K gets K,
which would be a silly thing to say,
but if I did,
maybe less silly would be
imagine an array of integers and
AsmI is being assigned AJ for
various values of I&J and
every so often, I and J are the same.
So AsmI gets ASI.
Anyway, let's just do
it with simple integer variable
K. Well, let's see then.
We take the value of
the right hand side, which is three.
We start in K,
wiping out the old value.
K is unchanged.
That's what people expect
self assignment to do.
If an object's being assigned to itself,
for one reason or another,
usually never is anything as silly
as this with the same variable on both sides,
but it happens a lot in
situations like this where you have
two expressions that sometimes
will end up indicating
actually the same object.
So when it happens,
the effect should be like nothing happened.
I mean, there should be no effect.
Assigning value an object to
itself should have no effect.
That's our goal.
So let's see what happens with our strings.
So let's say for example,
I have some string U and U has the value WOW
and I for one reason
or another, assign to itself.
So you gets. Again, we
never do it in
any way that's as silly as that.
I'd probably be some array of strings,
and we're assigning an object to it.
So I'm just using with
one particular variable here.
Okay.
Now remember that means take you and
call Opera requal with
the right hand side as an argument.
Okay, so the left hand side is
the objects that this pointer points to.
The right hand side is another name for you.
So what we have is
a pointer and a reference
both indicating the same objects.
So what does our code do?
Well, the first thing our code did was
get rid of the left hand sides old value.
So delete the text of
the object that this pointer points to.
Get rid of the left hand side is old value.
So call Delete on this pointer,
and that gets rid of that story.
Well, you can imagine that nothing
could work after that
because we lost the WOW.
If the whole point of
self assignment, I'm sorry,
I the whole result of
self assignment is supposed
to be that it looks like nothing changed,
something changed, we lost that text.
So so starting off by doing
the delete square bracket text
is going to lead us into Trump.
Now, let's see what we did after that.
The next statement we did was
to set the MLM to
the other guys to the right hand side
of MM. Oh, I'm sorry.
I'm sure somebody probably commented
on this and nobody told me.
I'm sorry. My parameters called RHS.
So, this should be RHS.
And this thing here should be RHS.
I copied and pasted and forgot
that I used
a different name for the variable.
So we assigned over the length,
so we'll take the right hand
side length, which is three,
store it in the len member
of the object that this pointer points to,
which is right here.
So we pick up three and store it back there.
Okay. That's harmless.
Then we set text
to a new array
of the appropriate number of characters.
Three plus one is four. So a brand new array
of four characters is allocated,
and we set this pointer to point to it.
Now,
these are uninitialized characters,
of course.
Then we did stir copy to
text of the right hand sides text.
Well, the right hand sides text
is this array.
And the left hand side text sorry,
and then Mtext is also that array.
Basically, we're string copying
this array into itself.
And that's going to be undefined behavior.
What's likeliest to happen
is your runtime system will simply say,
Okay, tell me where to copy from.
Tell me where to copy to, and I'll just copy
bytes until I copy a zero byte.
So what it will probably do is say,
Okay, I will copy
this bite into
the destination, which is the same place.
I'll copy this bite to itself,
and I'll stop if it's the zero byte.
If not, I'll go on to the next one and
copy it to itself and
stop if it's the zero byte,
then this one, then this one.
And I'll keep on going until I
happen to pick up and store a zero byte.
Maybe that'll happen in here.
Maybe that'll happen out of bounds with
the array because we
don't know what's in the storage here.
It's definitely undefined behavior.
It's not likely to crash.
It'll probably just pick up and
store bytes here and
run off the end of the array,
but keep on going until it happens
to come to a zero byte and store it.
So the assignment operator will probably not
crash and probably not
probably will return, okay.
But we're left in this weird state
where the old value of you was Wow.
Now it's not WOW and
that's not a valid C string.
And so, yeah, bad things
are going to happen surely from here on.
So we totally have
to prevent this from happening.
And let's see how we can do that.
So again, the original situation
was we had our Wow,
and we went wrong right away.
I mean, what's going to lead to trouble
right away is getting rid of the Wow.
And so, but
that's what we normally want to do,
except when
the objects being assigned to itself,
when an object is being assigned to itself,
we want to do one thing, and otherwise,
this code could work okay.
So we need to test for that.
And if we're going to
test for that, we discover
the object is going to be assigned to itself.
Well, then let's just return
immediately because it already
has the value we want to we
want it to end up having.
So the patterns going to be the object
if the left hand side object is
the same object as
the right hand side object,
then we can just return immediately.
Okay.
Okay. Let's try that.
So, now, how do I tell
if the left hand side object is
the right hand side object? Well, let's see.
Uh, The left hand
side object, the right hand side object.
So the right hand side object.
Well, Can I say that?
Well, that's not quite right because
this is a pointer to a string,
and that's a string,
and that's another name for a string.
The types aren't right.
That's a pointer to a string,
and that's a string.
Okay, so what I really want to say, Well,
how do I know if
the two strings are so this is not right.
Not quite right. How do
I know if these two strings
are really the same string?
Well, let's see.
If there are two strings,
it's like that, if
the left hand side is the same strength,
the same string, it looks like that.
If they're in the same place,
they must be the same string. Um,
Oh, okay. So let's look
at where they are. That's their address.
Oh, okay.
So if the address
of the left hand side string is this,
the address of the right hand string
is Ampersand RHS.
So that's how you ask if
the two strings are the same string.
If this pointer is
the same value as that pointer,
Ampersand or RHS would be
a pointer to this string here.
Are these pointer values the same?
Yeah, because they point to the same ojle.
Okay. So that'll work.
So all I have to do
here to make this at least correctly,
would be something like that.
I will now change my comment too.
This is now not the modern way to do it.
So this is an implementation
that will do the job,
but it's not the modern way to write it,
but I'll get to that in a second.
So the idea here is that, all right,
if the objects are not the same object,
then we have to do
the work that we did before.
If they are the same object,
then we skip all that.
And in all cases, we return Star T.
Okay.
So this is the way that
the assignment operator is
sort of the classic model for
how to write an assignment operator.
If you look at any C plus
plus text written before,
say, about 2000 2001, 2002.
And you still see it sometimes
in older C plus plus tutorials.
They give this is the pattern for
writing an assignment operator.
You verify
that the objects are not the same object.
If they are the same object,
you just return immediately.
But if they aren't the same object,
you do something to
clean up the left hand side.
In our case, it was to get rid of
the dynamically allocated text,
and then you do something to make
the left hand side look like
a copy of the right hand side.
So that was the classic model
for how to write an assignment operator.
It has an issue, and
I'll talk about that in a bit,
but let me just hit the questions
that almost always I mean,
without even looking at the questions,
I know what some of
the more common questions here are.
So let me address those.
So, again, this is the classic code,
and here are the kind
of questions that come up.
One of them is, well,
that test to see if
the strings are different.
I wrote that test as if this
is equal not equal to Ampersand RHS.
If the pointer to the left hand side object
is pointing to a different place
than the pointer to
the right hand side object.
If they point to different
places, they're different objects.
If they point to the same place,
they're the same object.
How do I know if the phrase
the governor of California and the phrase
Gavin Newsom are
talking about the same person.
One way to do it would be,
I'm going to go find where
the governor of California is, okay?
I go up Sacramento
and look at the state house, okay?
And there in the governor's office sitting in
his chair is some person.
That's the governor of California.
Now let's see. Where's Gavin Newsom?
Look around. Hey, where's Gavin Newsom?
Oh, he's over there.
Lo and they're sitting in
the same chair at
the same time is Gavin Newsom.
So since the governor of California is there
and Gavin Newsom is
there, they are the same person.
Okay. So that's checking
this exactly the same object.
Now, some people say, Well, okay, well,
how is that different from
saying if the object that this pointer
points to is not
equal to the right hand side object.
Well, that's asking a different question.
That's assuming this is a type string,
and this is a type string
or this was a type string pointer.
And this was a type string pointer.
That's a different question.
This question is comparing
two pointers to see if they
point to a different place or the same place.
This is comparing two strings,
and this will not compile unless you have
defined operator not equal
to let you compare two string objects.
This is actually comparing the values of
the strings if we
had defined such an operator.
That would not be
an unreasonable thing to do,
by the way, for the string type.
We could define an operator
double equal that takes
two strings and say compares their values.
The two strings are equal if say, you know,
their lengths are equal and if they have
the same characters up
to and including the zero byte.
That could be our implementation
of an operator double equal to string.
An operator not equal for strings,
two strings would give
you the opposite result.
So if we had such a thing,
this would compile, but it's not
testing are the two objects the same object?
It's saying, you know,
whether they're the same object or not,
do the two strings have the same value?
You might say, well, that's
not bad because if they
do have the same value,
if this is the string
hello and that's the string hello,
then there's no reason to actually
go through the work of doing the assignment.
You know, why do you need to
get rid of the old hello here,
copy over the length five
to replace this length five,
allocate a new array of six characters,
copy hello with a zero byte into there.
And now this has a pointer
to hello with the length five,
just like it was before
It's just like it was before.
So you could say,
if I replace
this condition with this condition,
assuming I have defined
a not equal operator for string,
this will still be correct code.
In fact, it will bypass
this work in more cases.
It will not only bypass
the work if two strings the two objects are
the same object because of course
they would have the same value,
but it would also bypass the work if
two different strings happen
to have the same value.
Then there's no reason to do any work
because this one already
looks like a copy of that one.
So you might say, maybe that's
a better thing because it
bypasses the work more often.
I would disagree because the cost of checking
two strings to see if they have
the same value is not totally trivial, right?
If two strings start off the same, you know,
they have the same length,
and they start off the same,
but then they differ somehow.
Well, you've gone through
a loop partway through the string to
check those characters and partway through,
you said, Oh, okay, they're different.
So the problem is, you did
a lot of work to find out, Oh, guess what?
They are different. And so
I'll go ahead and do this anyway.
So so you have to balance,
how often is it
the case that the two strings you're
assigning actually have the same
value versus,
you know, you have to balance
that against the cost of Yeah,
but how much does it cost to see
if two strings have the same value?
If it turns out it's not very common that
you do assignment with
two strings having the same value.
And you figure out the cost of
this work and how frequently that occurs,
you may find it's not worth that check.
It's not worth the check to see if
two strings have the same value so
that you could bypass this work
even if they were in different places.
Simply because that doesn't
happen often enough to make the cost
of doing that check every
time you assign two strings worthwhile.
So generally, we'll leave it this way.
We'll compare the pointers,
not the actual values of the string. Okay.
Another common thing people
wonder about is, Hey, you know,
I noticed that the the body
of this if statement is,
do what the destructor does,
followed by do what
the copy constructor does.
So could I somehow
in my implementation of
the assignment operator, you know,
call the destructor for the left hand side,
and then call the copy constructor
somehow to make the left hand side
look like a copy of the right hand side?
And the answer is technically, yes,
you could do that,
but have to do it exactly the right way,
and the way people think of
doing it is not the right way.
In other words, there are
language constructs in C plus plus you would
have to use to do this. We don't know them.
And so if you tried to do this way,
tried to do it that way, you
would probably get it wrong.
You might be able to
write something that compiles,
but it would not do the right thing.
The most common thing people try
to do is somehow, Oh,
I'm going to call the copy
instructor just by saying,
you know, string, open friend, whatever.
No, no, that's not going to work.
You
would constructing a temporary object that
gets immediately destroyed and having
no effect on the object
that this pointer points to.
So really,
the way you might try to
do this is not going to work.
So don't bother trying to
implement the assignment operator
by calling the copy constructor.
That's wrong. Calling the copy instructor
to directly do something to
the left hand side object.
That's not going to work out, right.
Oh, well, but I
don't like the fact
that the code is the same.
Do I have to write
the same code in two places?
No. I mean, one way, again,
an old classic way was,
well, maybe you have
a private helper function.
Maybe you have a private member function that
both the copy constructor
and the assignment operator call
and the private function does
this dirty work. That could work.
But the modern way is
actually solving another problem,
which unfortunately we don't
know enough to know
the implications
of the classical way of doing it.
But let me just briefly mention it.
So one of
the problems with the assignment operator,
one of the problems with
both the copy constructor
and the assignment operator is at some point,
we dynamically allocate some new storage.
What if that fails?
What if there's not enough
memory to make a copy
of the right hand side for the new object?
Well, then an exception is thrown.
Okay, now, we don't
know how to deal with exceptions,
so this is not going to be something
that we'd have to face.
But there are programs
that do know how to deal with exceptions,
and they might discover, Oh,
if an exception was thrown we tried
to do something because
there was limited memory,
maybe we could do something to clean
up memory and try the operation again.
But for that to work right, you'd
really like it to be the case
that if some operation like
your assignment operator or cop constructor
fails and throws an exception,
ideally, it should leave
all the variables that you will
still exist after the function
leaves from the exception,
leave all those variables unchanged,
or at least, in a valid state.
And with this implementation
of the assignment operator,
that's not going to happen.
So very briefly because
it's not really within
the scope of the class,
the issue is, if and I said,
UGS, And so we tried this,
and if we were to
go through this code here, we'd say,
well, let's see, the
objects have different objects.
So let's delete the old value of
you Let's assign over the five to here.
So use length is now five.
Let's now give you its own text.
So let's dynamically allocate an array of
six characters. Let's say that fails.
There's not enough memory.
I mean, there could be
plenty for other types,
there could be plenty of other reasons
why somebody could throw an exception.
Ours is going to be
running out of memory here.
We run out of memory,
so an exception is thrown.
Now, what that does is it says, essentially,
further execution of the assignment
operator code is abandoned,
and the exception comes back
up to this level of code,
and maybe this level of
code will catch it or deal with it.
If not, send it up to something higher.
But anyway, when we come
back up to this level of code,
look what happens. Look what we've got.
We've got a variable U,
remember, U was declared here.
We've got a variable U, a string variable,
but its value is bizarre.
U has a dangling pointer here.
And the problem is, for example,
if this code doesn't
handle the exception either,
and so the exception has to go
up to some higher level code,
local variables
still have their destructors call.
As an exception, it's going to
be passed up to a higher level,
local variables have their destructors call.
When the destructor for you is
called on this dangling pointer,
undefined behavior,
our program probably crashes.
So the problem is this implementation
of the assignment operator makes
some serious changes to
the left hand side object
before it can be
sure I'll finish successfully.
We might throw an exception later on,
leaving the left hand side object
in a horrible state.
So so again, fixing
that is beyond the scope
of the class to
worry about all the exception details,
but we can show you a fix
that is something that will fix
the problem and will also be
a nice simple way
to write an assignment operator.
So we're going to do this by
essentially causing the order
of these things to be rearranged somehow.
We don't get rid of the old
guys text until we
have a we're sure
that we got the new storage.
We're not going to make changes to
the left hand side until we're
sure that we're not going
to throw an exception.
To do that we'll introduce
a new function to help us.
I'm going to show you the modern way
to write an assignment operator.
It's going to make use of one more function.
So let me go back up here to the declaration
of the string type
and introduce that function.
It's a swap function.
And basically, it allows you
to swap one string with another string.
And its implementation.
I won't go through the full implementation.
It's pretty straightforward.
Now, the goal of the swap function is if
one string has one text in
its length and another string
has another text in its length,
after the swap function,
those should have changed places.
So all we need to do is really
just swap the text pointers
and swap the lengths.
So some code to swap
the pointers and swap the lengths.
So let me illustrate the swap function
first and then see how it
solves our assignment problem.
If I have two strings,
let's say A and B.
And let's say A has the text, hello.
And it's five characters long,
and B has the text,
Wow and it's three characters long.
And I want to swap those strings.
I want B to end up
having the five character string hello,
and A having the three character string. Wow.
Okay.
Let me do the thing
that's pictorially easiest first.
My implementation of swaps said
we just swap the pointers
and swap the integers.
So how do you swap integers?
If I have two integers and I want to
swap their values, how do I do it?
Well, I don't just assign this one over
here and then this one over here because
if this were three and this were five,
if I assign the three to the five,
and then that's now three,
assign it back to the three, I lost the five.
So, of course, we know, oh,
to swap two integers,
we need a third variable,
and we will simply
set up that third variable,
say as a copy of this one, and
then assign the five over here,
and then assign
that temporary variable over here.
And now we've swapped the five into three.
So swapping two values,
simple built in types is really easy.
You just have another variable that type and
just do this little three way exchange.
So we do that.
I have a temporary integer
and I initialize it say to the three,
then I can assign the five over to here,
and then I can assign
the temporary over to here.
And I swap the integers. Three statements.
The simple statements swap the integers.
I'll do the same thing for pointers.
I'll have a temporary pointer to character,
a temporary pointer to character,
and I'll initialize it with this pointer,
and then I'll assign this pointer over to
here so that B no longer
points to WOW but
gets a copy of A's pointer,
we assign that to there.
Then I'll assign the temporary over to A.
Same thing I did with the integers
except this time we do it with the pointers.
That value gets assigned over to here.
I'm doing this badly. Okay. All right.
So this pointer got assigned over to here,
so A now points to WOW.
And when we leave our swap function,
the local variables go away,
the local integer, the local pointer go away.
And A points to WOW with a length of three,
and B points to hello with a length of five.
They have indeed been swapped.
Notice, all we did
was three statements to switch two integers,
three statements to switch two pointers.
Was there any new dynamic allocation?
No. Was there any deletion?
No. So operations involving
simple built in types
like this can't throw exceptions.
So swapping two strings with
our swap function will
correctly swap their values
and not throw any exceptions.
Okay, so we got the swap function.
So now what I want to do is figure out,
how do I do assignment in
a way that's going to work out nicely.
A, you don't have to know anything
about exceptions or anything like that.
I'm just going through
the thought process that
led to the modern way
to write an assignment operator.
Okay. So here's the idea.
The first thing we
do in our assignment operator,
once we know that they're not
the same object is
we create a temporary string
as a copy of the right hand side.
So we're going to
create a new string as
a copy of the right hand side.
Well, that's okay.
So here's say a temporary string
as a copy of the right hand side.
It's a copy of the right hand side.
Notice that that's going
to call the copy constructor somehow,
and that's going to
dynamically allocate storage here.
If it can't get the storage,
if an exception is thrown because we can't
get the storage from the dynamic allocation,
then we never got this far.
We never got the storage, and we leave
the assignment operator and
notice is unchanged.
So unlike the classic way
to write the assignment operator,
if we can't get
the storage as a copy of the hello,
we leave the function, and there's
no dangling pointer anywhere. We're fine.
If we succeed in
getting the storage for the temporary,
we're now going to finish the job
without doing
anything that could throw an exception.
And how are we going to do that? Very simple.
We're going to swap the value
of Temp and the value of.
So after swapping, so again,
you know, the swap function we go,
we'll exchange the integers.
And exchange the pointers.
No new dynamic allocation, exchanges here.
So ten points to WOW and points to Hello.
So after doing the swap,
has the old value of Temp,
which is a copy of the right hand side,
and Temp has the old value of HU.
Well, we've achieved the goal of assignment.
Y now has its own copy of the text of S and
the old looks like a copy of
S and has its own storage.
And that's great.
So all that has to happen is
for the local temp to be destroyed,
'cause when temp is destroyed,
that will get rid of the WOW
and then Tep goes away.
That works.
So, the implementation there says, All right.
Let's go look at the modern way to do this.
Let's create a temporary string
as a copy of the right hand side.
And on the left hand side object,
let's call the swap function
to swap it with the temporary.
And this closed curly
brace leaves the scope of the I statement,
which will cause when
we leave the scope of the if statement,
the temporary will be destroyed,
so that causes the destructor.
And there we go. That's it.
That is the modern way
to write an assignment operator.
This is the so called copy and swap approach.
It's really amazing. It's beautiful.
You've always wanted to, you know,
have the assignment operator
call the copy constructor somehow.
Well, it does it by
constructing a temporary string
as a copy of the right hand size.
So that does, in fact,
get the copy constructor called.
We don't have to have the I'm sorry,
the copy constructors down here.
We don't have to have this key code
written in more than one place.
That's the code for the copy constructor,
and that's the only place we write it.
And then our assignment operator will make
use of that to create the temporary object.
And that will try to
acquire storage to make a copy.
And if it fails and throws
an exception, we haven't changed anything.
If it succeeds, then all we have to do is put
the copied right hand side in
the proper place and
we do that by swapping it.
And the swap doesn't
do anything that can throw an exception
because it's just moving integers
around and moving pointers around.
There's nothing harmful there.
So there we go.
The modern pattern for
writing an assignment operator for
any type follows
pretty much exactly this approach.
For whatever type, in this case,
it happens to be string.
The signature of your function is you take
a constant reference to the right hand side
because you promise not to
modify the right hand side,
and you're going to return a reference,
which will be the return star this,
a reference to the left hand side,
and the body pretty much looks like this.
If the objects are different objects,
then we'll copy the right hand side
to a temp and then
swap it into the right place.
And the destructor will
get rid of the old value of
the left hand side because the old value of
the left hand side is sitting in the temp at
the time we destroy TEM.
If the objects are the same type
the same object,
then we skip all that and
just return star this.
But actually, if the objects are
the same object, this would still work.
So this if test is
not necessary for correctness.
It's just a bit of an optimization.
Because if the objects are the same object,
if you work through the code,
if I have the left hand side
and the right hand side object are the same,
then I simply copy the right hand side into a
temporary and then swap
it back in with the left hand side,
which is also the right hand side.
So we basically made a copy of
the value and then
swapped it back into itself.
So that was, you know,
wasteful, but at least it works.
So the test for
self assignments not
so necessary in this case.
But this is the pattern that people
these days now write assignment operators.
It requires having a swap function,
that itself does not well,
the swap function for string should not
call the assignment operator for string,
should not call the
copy constructor for string.
Swap should simply work
itself on the data members itself.
It defeats the purpose if
SWAP calls assignment for string
because string
is the assignment for strings is
going to be calling Swap.
So that's kind of silly.
And it defeats the purpose
of SWAP calls the copy constructor for
string because that's going to try to
dynamically allocate stuff that might fail,
and the whole point is we don't
want we don't want
the SWAP function to
do anything that might fail.
So the swap function should be written
to simply do the swaps on the data members.
And then we've got a pattern
that works very nicely for writing
an assignment operator that leverages
the code of the copy constructor
without having to
actually duplicate that code.
Okay, so that is
the last bit of the resource
management stuff I wanted to get into.
You know, the basic ideas
here carry over for lots of other types.
As I said, for our purposes,
the main resource we're going to be
managing when we write our own types,
it tends to be memory,
but it could be all kinds of other things
like open file descriptors or locks on
database records or any other sort
of resource that you might have
to allocate and deallocate,
which means you'd have to write a destructor.
And if you need to write
a destructor for a type,
you quite often will have to write
a copy constructor and an
assignment operator to get correct behavior.
Because the reason to write a destructor is
usually there's a resource I want to release.
But then that also means, well,
then how do I copy the
object if it holds a resource?
Do I want the compiler just to do a member by
member copy of the data members
or do I need to take control myself?
So generally,
these three functions, the destructor,
the assignment operator,
destructor, the copy constructor,
and the assignment operator tend
to all travel together.
If you need one, you're
generally going to need the other two.
There are some exceptions, but
that's generally going to
be the way it works.
Now, what that tells you, for example,
although I think we mentioned it
in a footnote in the Project one spec,
is that project one is kind of
deficient in this regard, because after all,
if you have a room object
and this room object has
an array of pointers to Bs Okay.
Now, we have a destructor that
says when a room object is going away,
we have to loop through the array of
pointers to bees for as many as
there are and call delete
on each of these pointers
to get rid of the bees.
That's fine. That deletions fine.
But we never wrote a copy constructor.
We never wrote an assignment operator.
We didn't need to copy or assign rooms.
But maybe this class can be used as part of
some fancier game where
we do need to say copy rooms.
If you want to be
careful because look what happens.
If we create another
room as a copy of this one,
then here's another room
and it has this array.
If we don't write a copy constructor,
the compiler writes one for
us that simply copies each member.
If this is a ten by 15 room,
say one member has the number of rows,
one member has the number of columns,
and there are other data members as well.
So if you don't write a copy constructor,
here's what will happen.
The one the compiler writes for us will copy
the integer, copy the integer,
and then it's got a copy the array,
which it does by copying each member,
copy the pointer, copy
the pointer, copy the pointer.
So the problem is the new room shares
the same bees as the old room.
That's going to be
a problem because, of course,
when we're done with that copied room and
that copied room is about to go away,
the destructor is going to
go through the array and
call delete on each of the pointers here,
and then this can go right now.
This can go right now. This go away now.
But the original room now
has a bunch of dangling pointers,
and when the destructor
is called in this room,
delete is going to be called on all these
dangling pointers, undefined behavior.
So if a room contains pointers
to dynamically allocated bees,
then we have to think carefully about
the copying and assignment behavior
of the room type.
So we didn't clutter
your mind with that in Project one,
and certainly we didn't clutter
people in CS 31 with that.
But realistically,
that's what you would want to do.
Right. So if you need a destructor,
you probably need to think
about copying an assignment as well.
Okay? So, finally, I want to
hit an issue that comes up when
you're dealing with assignment,
but it's actually much more general.
So looking back at assignment of
strings with the
old fashioned implementation,
remember that if I write
an expression U gets
S using the assignment operator,
that really means call the member function.
And here was
an implementation of the member function,
the old fashioned implementation,
look like this.
We clean up the left hand side,
and we copy over the right
hand side, that'll work.
Now, it's not going to
work correctly in the face of exceptions.
The new can't do its job,
that's why we tend to use
the modern style of copy and swap.
But the key point is,
if we don't check for self assignment here,
if we don't check that the object that
the left hand side pointer is pointing to is
different from the object that
the right hand side is a reference to,
this code was problematic.
I went through that. We'd be
deleting the text for
the left hand side value,
but if that's the same object
as the right hand side value,
we just lost that text
from the right hand side value.
So the problem comes if
the left hand side value is
the same object as the right hand side value.
For example, let's say that
we've got an array of strings and we
have some algorithm that's going through
and assigning the string
at position J of the array
to the string at position I of the array.
And what happens, of course, this means that.
But what happens if I happens
to be equal to J at some point?
Then that means that the left hand side,
SSI, well, that's what
the this pointer is going to point
to in this call here.
And the right hand side object,
SAs J, that's going to
be the same object as SA sabi.
So RHS, the parameter RHS will be
a reference to SACBI the same object.
This is called aliasing.
When you have two or more ways
of talking about the same object.
Coming from the normal use of the word alias,
typically a criminal will have an alias.
They will use they'll have their real name.
So, for example, James Bulger,
whose nickname was Whitey Bulger,
was a Boston crime boss,
active from being a kid in the 1940s.
And then he went into hiding in the 1990s
and ended living in
Santa Monica under
the alias of Charles Gasco.
So Charles Gasco is
an alias for the person
whose real name is James Bolger.
He was actually ultimately caught.
So anyway, in a computer science context,
this would mean if you've got two ways of
talking about the same object
perhaps as maybe you have a pointer,
two pointers pointing to the same object
or a pointer in reference to the same object,
then that would be an example there.
So this happens here
in this assignment operator,
and this function has
as a parameter a reference to a string.
And so whenever aliasing
occurs, you've got to ask yourself,
is my code correct if
these two ways of talking about
an object are actually
talking about the same object.
And so we found that
our original implementation was, no,
that was not correct if this pointer points
to the same object that
the RHS reference is referring to.
And that led us to realize,
Oh, we have to fix that here.
Now, this can come up in
all sorts of situations.
So let's say we have some kind
of financial application,
and we have a function
that we use to transfer
money from one account to another.
So here's this transfer function.
You give it the account
you're transferring thought from,
the account you're transferring to,
and the amount you want to transfer.
And so it seems like
the straightforward algorithm is, well,
if the amount you want to transfer is
more than the balance
of the account you're transferring from,
we should write an error message.
There's not enough money to do the transfer.
Otherwise, we'll debit
from account by that amount,
subtract the amount from the from account,
and we'll credit
the two account with that amount.
We'll add that amount to the two account.
Okay, this looks
really pretty obviously correct.
This seems to be the correct behavior.
But we have
a situation where aliasing occurs.
In this function, we
have two references to accounts.
What if they're the same account?
So you should always be asking yourself about
this when you have a function.
Be on the lookout for
two pointers or references to the same type.
That means aliasing might occur,
and you want to make sure your code is
correct in the case that aliasing can occur.
So it happens here because we have
two references to account.
It happened the assignment operator,
a little more subtly,
as a member function,
this pointer will be a pointer to a string,
and there's a parameter
that's a reference to a string.
So this function could have aliasing
occurring if the pointer
and the reference are
talking about the same object.
And, of course, we saw that
and we fixed it because it was incorrect.
So what happens here?
What happens if I try to
transfer money from an account to itself?
What if we end up calling transfer, say,
we have an array of accounts,
so we have some algorithm that's
moving money around between the arrays,
and this algorithm is at
various times transferring money
from A subi the account array,
subi to a sub J,
and we're transferring $20,000 around.
Okay, or some amount.
Well, again, if I is equal to J,
these are actually the same account,
and so we're transferring $20,000
from an account to itself.
Now, you might say,
well, that should be harmless.
I mean, if you're just moving
money from an account to itself,
you're not really moving money at all.
So let's see what happens here.
Well, if the account has,
say, $40,000 in it,
then we're going to subtract
$20,000 from the account
and then credit it with $20,000.
So it ends up with the same amount of money,
$40,000. So it looks harmless.
Well, yes and no.
In that case, it's harmless, but maybe not.
You know, what if the account only
has $5,000 in it?
Well, then we're going to
write an error message
or is it going to say, Hey, guess what?
You can't transfer $20,000
from this account to itself.
Well, yeah, but really, so what?
If it's only got $5,000,
that's not really a transfer.
So you might question whether
writing an error message is appropriate here.
Or there might be circumstances
where maybe debiting money
from an account maybe
the bank charges a slight fee for that.
So if you don't actually do a real transfer,
if you're actually not really transferring
money because it's the same account,
then should you be charged the fee for
a transfer when there really was for a debit,
because there really was no debit
because you just credited it right back.
And even worse, suppose
that there's a law that
says that if at least
$10,000 is being transferred
from one account to another,
a form has to be filed with the government,
maybe to help trace
money laundering or something like that.
So our code could be, Okay, we'll fix that.
We'll say if the amounts at least $10,000,
then we're going to
file some form with the government.
The problem is, again,
if you're not really transferring
money because it's from
an account to the same account,
then you really shouldn't be filing the form.
There is no transfer
of money going on, really.
It's staying in the same account.
So, you know, that's
an unnecessary form you're
filing with the government.
Now, you might say, so what?
Well, there are laws in effect that
say that filing too
many frivolous forms with the government,
you know, could earn you a fine.
For example, there's actually
a federal law that makes it a
crime subject to a fine and
possibly imprisonment to file
a frivolous tax return.
There are various tax protesters
who believe, for example,
the 16th Amendment, which authorizes
the income tax was improperly passed.
It's unconstitutional to have
an income tax, a federal income tax.
Therefore, they will protest this
by filing you know,
silly returns with the government
hoping to overload
them with all these
silly income tax returns, et cetera.
Well, the government says you can't do that.
That's a crime to file
a frivolous tax return.
So, you know,
maybe there's something that says,
if you file forms for
this money laundering tracing law,
if you file forms that aren't
really transfers, that's frivolous.
And if there's too many of those,
we will find your company.
So there could be
consequences for ignoring alias.
So at the very least,
you should consider the issue
and check your implementation and see
if your implementation does
the right thing in the event of aliasing.
And so I would argue that
while at first glance,
it seems harmless, if you
transfer money from an account
to itself, so what?
It's not a real transfer. That's fine.
Well, you might want to rule that out.
So we might just decide to
protect this whole thing with, say,
if the from account
is different from the two account.
And how do we know they're different?
Because they're in
different places in memory?
If the From account is
different from the two account,
then do all this work.
But if they're the same thing,
the same account, then do nothing.
It's not really a transfer.
Okay, so the bottom line
is you should always,
always be on the lookout for aliasing.
If a function can be
called with two pointers or
references to the same type,
aliasing might occur.
Make sure your implementation
takes care of that in an appropriate way.
There have been plenty of programs that
have been just fine until one day,
somebody did something involving
aliasing and oops,
that algorithm doesn't work correctly,
and so the program did bad.
So that wraps up what I want to
say about resource management,
and I'll end the recording here.