Today I want to look at a
little bit more about
separate compilation and some issues coming
up that will be relevant for, for project 1.
So what we looked at last time
was issues of separate compilation.
What happens is the compiler
takes each of your source files,
it compiles it producing an object file.
And with the object file contains
is the translation of
the code in your source file.
It's a translation of
the code for all the functions.
You've got.
Any sort of global objects,
not local variables,
but the global objects
predominantly for most people that will
be things like Libre
has global objects like std,
colon, colon C out.
We're not making much use of
global variables except
perhaps global constants.
So, so our object files and we have
a global constant that'll
be, that'll be in there.
And then there'll be two lists,
a list of the names that we define.
So functions we implement
global variables we declare,
and global names that we need.
So if a source file
calls a function and
it needs to be defined somewhere,
the implementation has to be somewhere
that'll be in the list of needs.
And so the linker brings everything together,
tying it together along with the,
the libraries and the
rules for linking we talked about.
You can't have more than
one definition for something.
So you can't implement
the exact same function
with the same number of arguments,
same types of arguments, more than once.
In particular, you can't have
more than one main routine and
every knee has to be
satisfied by some definition.
And so I and I noted the linker will give
you error messages if
you violate this, if you,
if you call a function that you'd
never implemented anywhere down,
the compiler will give you some message about
an unresolved external reference
or an undefined reference,
an undefined name, something like that.
If you define something more than once,
you'll get something
about multiple definitions.
So let me look at some issues
involved with
separate compilation that come up here.
So let me bring up a,
again, we have some graphics application.
And so here's what I want to try to do.
I have a dot h which defines
a point class that was provided.
We're providing for people.
Circle dot h defines a circle type.
In particular, circles are implemented
using point in order
to specify the center of the circle.
So circle dot h
is going to make use of quaint.
Now, a client may try to do this.
I want to use a circle.
And so the simple rule
for clients to remember,
the one you want it to be implementing.
Simple rule should be,
if I want to use a tight,
I'll include the appropriate header
that defines that time.
That's the simple rule.
If I want to use a circle,
I should just have to include
circle dot h and that's good enough.
Well, we try this, of course,
it won't compile.
When the compiler tries to process
myapp dot CPP and comes to 0,
you're including circle dot h.
Okay?
I will remember where
I am and come back here.
Let's go process circle dot h, circle.
That says, okay, here's what it
means to be a circle, okay?
And at that point, what's a point?
And so the compiler will give you
a compilation error about this line.
It doesn't know what a point is.
Now, the wrong way to
fix that would be to say,
oh, hey, people who were using my,
my, my graphics library.
Want to use a circle,
you need to include
point dot h and circle dot
h. And you have to include
point dot h before you
and you include circle dot h.
So if that's my rule,
I tell people and
they do that, this will be fine.
The compiler will first include point dot h,
which provides a definition
of what it means to be a point.
Then when it gets to circle dot h,
the compiler says, Okay,
fine, you're defining a circle.
I know what a point is.
Everything's fine.
And so now we have it, we have a circle here.
But that's a terrible thing
to do to your users.
If you're the designer
and the graphics library,
you have a whole complicated set of rules.
If I want to use, if you want to
use appoint conclude point dot h.
If you want to use a circle,
you have to include point dotage and
circle that h in that order.
And that leads to a whole bunch of rules.
If you want to use a blob object,
you have to include these other
three had header files in a certain order.
That's, that's too much to remember.
You want this simple rule.
The simple rule is,
if you want to use a circle,
include circle dot h.
If you want to use oblige,
include blood RH, and
you shouldn't have to know anything else.
Because after all, if I'm a user,
a circle, I would ask you,
why do I have to include point dot h?
I'm not talking about points,
I'm talking about cerebral.
And if your answer is a well,
But circle is implemented using a point,
then you say, well, why do I care?
I'm using a circle, I should not
care about how it's implemented.
So, so the solution
is if a header file
in order to compile successfully,
needs to know about some other,
some other types, then
the header file should be
responsible for making sure
that both those names are defined.
So if circle at
H is going to be talking about points,
it should be on circle dot h to
include point dot h
to make sure that happens.
Yeah, our clients is very simple rule,
if you want to use a circle,
include circle dot h.
So what will happen of course is
this will now work the compiler
when compiling myapp dot cpp,
we'll start by saying,
okay, I'll, I'll include circle at H.
Then I'll continue circle about
age being included starts off
by saying I'm going to include point dot h.
So find the compiler
processes the declaration of points.
So now we know what a point is and now
continues and processes
the declaration of circle,
knowing what a point is.
So, so everything's fine.
By the time we're done with circle dot h,
We know what a surplus.
We also happen to know what a point
is that was incidental.
But, but we know what a circle is,
so, so we're happy.
Okay.
Well, that's not the whole story.
What if the client also wants to use a point?
So I want to have a
pointed at some coordinate,
say x-coordinate 2, y coordinate
for whatever the point constructor uses.
So as a client I say,
well, let's see. If I want.
The simple rule that I
know is if I want to use a circle,
I'll include circle dot
h. If I want to use a point,
I'll include point dot
h. Because I should
not have to know as a client of this type,
I should not have to know that
circle is implemented using point.
Circle might be implemented
not using point, maybe.
The circle type doesn't use
point at all. It just has two doubles.
I don't have to know.
I shouldn't have to know that.
Well, unfortunately, if I
if I tried to finding
this, this won't compile.
What happens when I process,
when I compile myapp dot cpp,
the compiler says, Okay,
you want to include circle dot h, fine.
So I'll start by including circle dot h,
which starts by including point dot h. So
we have a declaration of point, okay?
And now we finish up circle dot h, Okay?
We know what a point is all as well.
And so when we come out
of this declaration of
this include a circle dot
h. We know what a point is,
we know what a circle is.
But then we include point dot h here.
So the compiler processes this declaration of
the point type and
that's going to lead to a compilation error.
The reason being that if you're compiling
a file and the file
defines say, some class a.
And later on in the file,
we also define the name a again,
even if it's identical,
even if the deck with whatever
the implementation of the type
a or whatever the declaration
the type a was here.
And then it, even if
it's identical down later,
That's a compilation error in the same file.
You can't when compiling the same file,
you can't have more than one
declaration of the full,
the full, full declaration of the type a.
And that's what's happening here.
What's happening up here is when
compiling myapp dot cpp,
we see a declaration
of the point class because
circle dot h includes
point DOD aids and
therefore there's a declaration
of the point type.
And then later on we have it again.
When we include point out a second time.
Okay, Again, the wrong solution
is to say, oh,
your ear to the designer and
the graphics class and your
documentation says,
if you want to use a circle
includes circle dot h.
If you want to use a point,
use point dot h. But if you want to
use both of them in the same file,
don't include point dot h,
just include circled audience.
Again, that's getting too
complicated for users to know.
Users should not have to know what circle
depends on and therefore whether or not
you should also include point dot h to pay.
It's a, it's a pain.
You don't want to, don't want to do that.
So what we need is a way to somehow say,
for the second and
any further input inclusions of point dot h,
We don't really want to process the,
the declaration of the points.
So in other words, we need a way to
say after the first time,
we've included point dot h and
we've seen this point declaration
later on if we ever include
point dot h Again in
this compilation of this file,
don't process this declaration.
So this is where
things get kind of strange
as far as the standard goes.
We, we don't have
a way in standard C or C plus plus to say,
don't process this more than once.
Or we don't have a way to do
that in a simple way.
The way that was
kind of a work around for the problem in C.
Almost 50 years ago,
is still the only way that will
standardly guaranteed to work
across all implementations of the compilers.
So the way that,
that's done is something like this.
The first time we process point dot h,
We essentially drop a marker.
We'll see how that works.
We somehow mark that we've been here before.
And then in any implement
to end anytime we include point dot h,
We check, have we been here before?
If we've been here
before, then skip everything.
So the way to do that is in point dot h,
We will make use of the, the,
the, the pound define
syntax available to us to define some symbol.
Now, what's that symbol?
It doesn't matter. It could be any symbol.
I will pick a symbol that somehow tied
to the name of
the class we're defining
or the name of the file,
I'll call it say point included.
But I could pick any other name.
So I pick a name.
By convention,
we put it in all capital letters.
And now I'm defining it,
this, defining it as what?
Well, the general pound define lets you
define a symbol to be replaced by
other text that's not relevant here.
I just want to mark it as
your defined point included will be defined.
So whenever I process point dot h,
the first time we'll define that symbol.
Now we want to make sure we don't
process point that age more than once.
So I surround
all the significant code and point dot h,
I surround it with,
with this almost pointless.
And second, an F and
F on top and down at the end, an end.
Now endif is not allowed to
have anything significant after it.
But I tend, but you can put a comment and
so I tend to repeat what this is closing off.
It's closing off B, B,
B this if NDF up here for point included.
So that's a mouthful.
What's going on here?
The pound in if, if,
if n depth is asking,
if it's not defined,
the end is short for not,
the depth is short for define.
So if it's, if it's,
if it's not defined,
this symbol point included.
Another words, if point included has
not yet been defined,
then we are going to process everything
up to the corresponding end
up for the if and death.
So the offend f has a corresponding endif.
Everything in here is
controlled by that, that test.
So the test is if
the symbol has not yet been defined,
then do all this,
which is define it,
and then go ahead and process the code here
to just see what
the point class is all about.
So that solves the problem.
Here's, here's what's going on.
So here's what happens when we
compile myapp dot cpp.
We say, okay, let's include circle dot hhs,
circled IDA set circle dot h says,
Okay, let's include point dot h. We,
so this is the very first time.
Now when compiling this file,
it's the very first time we've done this.
We've included circle dot h.
So include point dot h ad.
That starts off by saying,
has the symbol point
included been defined yet?
No, it hasn't.
We have not.
During compiling this file.
We have not seen it defined yet.
So it says, okay, it's not defined.
Therefore, we're going to
process all this text.
So the compiler will say, Okay,
I will mark quaint included as being defined.
Defined as what? We don't
care if it's marked as
being defined and will
process the declaration of the coin class.
Okay, so now we know what a point is.
Alright, So we come back from here,
the symbol point included has been defined.
We know what a point is.
So now we can go ahead and
process the declaration of circle.
We know what a point is, everything's fine.
And when we finish here,
we come back out here.
And having included a circle dot h,
we have the symbol
point included being defined.
We know what a point, the point class is,
we know what the circle classes.
So now if we ever include point dot h again,
during compiling this file
which we're doing here.
Let's see if the symbol point
included is not defined.
Oh wait, it is defined.
All right, so we skip all this.
In particular, we skip
processing the point class declaration again.
And so we come out of this immediately,
having done nothing additional we make,
we haven't done anything new.
We still know that
the symbol point include is defined.
We still know what a point is,
we still know what a circle is.
And so now this code compiles fine.
We know what a circle is,
we know what appointed.
So that's the solution
from almost 50 years ago.
That is still the only
solution to this problem that
is guaranteed to be
portable across all compilers.
I mean, there are other techniques
that many compilers that introduced.
So just one line you can say
something pound pragma once at that,
that solves the problem, but that's not
portable across all compilers.
So we're not going to be using
that back project one
forbids you from using pragma once.
Some notes about this,
first of all terminology.
So this sort of thing is
called an Include Guard.
It's guarding against this file being
included more than once in the same,
in compiling the same file.
So in compiling myapp dot cpp,
the Include Guard for point dot h
is protecting us from from
including point dot h by
a circle dot h and
also directly including it ourselves.
No problem there.
Everything significant should be
inside the Include Guard.
Everything.
Don't try to do little things like, oh,
outside here I am and
start doing something significant
like declaring a class, foo and whatever.
But it's not no, that's outside.
Don't do it.
Everything significant
goes inside the Include Guard.
The only thing you would possibly put outside
the Include Guard would
be whitespace or a comment.
So maybe I want to
put a note in my file that
this is point Daddy's.
A comment can go outside there,
everything else signifigant should
be inside the Include Guards.
I emphasize that because I have seen
people try to put things
outside the Include Guards to,
to solve some, to attempt
to solve some problem they're
having and compiling.
And that's not the right way to do.
Everything goes inside of the Include Guard.
Also, because this could
happen in other levels.
This should be done with every
header file you write.
So for circle dot h,
I should have an Include Guard.
Why do I have an Include
Guard on circle dot h?
I'm certainly not including circle dot
h more than once in this compilation.
No, I'm not.
But there might be some other header I
include that itself includes
circle dot h. So if I include
that other header and I include circle dot h,
I want to make sure that I'm guarded against
the multiple definition of a circle type.
Now, you want the symbol to be
different from any other symbol you're using.
For example, if I were to
pick the symbol point included,
which is wrong, I mean, I could do that,
but look what happens if I happened to
pick a symbol I've used in a different file,
which can happen by
accident if you copy and paste.
So be careful.
Well, this is not going to work now
because when I include circle dot h,
It starts off by saying,
have I seen a declaration of
point included? No, I haven't.
So let's define point included.
Then. Include point dot h,
which says, oh, have I
seen a definition of point included?
Yes, I have. So skip all
this and then we end up not knowing
what a point is and we get a compilation down
here when we come to come to point.
So, so no, no, no.
Every file should have
a unique name for its Include Guard.
Now you have to make up, so you have to
make up a different name for each file.
And the common convention
is to make up a name that
somehow incorporates the filename
because your files are
going to have different names.
So if you incorporate the filename
somehow into your,
your Include Guard name,
then that'll make it different.
So my file circle dot h.
So why don't I call this circle include.
I'm probably not going to have
another file called circle.
So, so that would be a good way to,
to make sure it's kinda unique.
And I don't have to,
but if I want to,
I can put a comment here.
Be very, very careful
that the symbol you're testing
against the same as
the symbol you're defining
for this Include Guard.
I have over and over seen people do
things like like this,
where the symbol they're defining
is called point in coal did,
because they had a little typo there
and they switch the EU and the L.
But that's not the symbol
they're testing against.
And so they're going to have a problem
if they point dot h
is included more than once.
The symbol point included
will never be defined.
So you're always going to
try to do this twice
because the symbol you're defining
as point in cold it.
So, so make sure that the, you,
you, you, you have used the same symbol here.
Now again, this is
the point that the purpose of
the Include Guards is to
guard against including the same header
more than once in the same file.
So myapp dot CPP is including
circle dot h as including
point dot agents and circle
that h includes point dot h,
where including point that age
more than once in the same file.
This proof, this protects us.
It has absolutely nothing to do with
the fact that, you know,
one CPP file might include
point dot h and another CPP file.
And in the same program
you're building also includes
point that age that's
totally around, that totally separate.
Compiling myapp dot CPP is a distinct AC
from compiling some other CPP file
that happens to include point dot h,
include guards are irrelevant for that.
That's, that's,
that's not where it comes into play.
The Include Guard comes into
play when we're including
the same header file
more than once in compiling,
one given file, more than
once in compiling myapp dot cpp,
we're including point I'd age.
That's why it's relevant.
All the standard headers have include guards.
So if you are compiling a program and
you say include iostream,
either directly or indirectly,
and later on you
have another, include iostream.
Effectively.
That's harmless in the same header file,
including a standard header
more than once as harmless.
So that's one issue here.
Does that solve all our problems?
No, there's another compilation
problem to deal with.
So let me, let me go down here.
And let's say that we're writing
some application for the registrar.
And so let's say
that the registrar has decided that
we are going to have a class student
and students can enroll in courses.
So we'll have an enroll function
that takes a pointer to a course.
And the students study list will
be an array of pointers
to the courses the student,
students enrolled it. Okay?
We also have information about a course.
A given course has a certain number of units,
for example, associated with it.
And the a given course object
can have a roster
of all the students enrolled in the course.
So let's say we use an array
of pointers to each student there.
So for example,
the student Fred might
have a pointer to the course.
Cs 32 might have a pointer
to the course for, or physics.
You know, what?
A, might have a pointer
to a course for Math 33 be.
Now the course object,
for example, for CS 32,
that for the CS 32 course object will have
the Unix function returning
for it's a four unit course.
And we'll have a pointer to each of
the students enrolled in CS 32.
Okay? So we might
want to have some function that takes
a student and a pointer
to some student and a pointer to
some course and enrolls
that student in the course.
So we'll take the student object,
we'll call the enrolled member function.
Now if we try to compile this,
of course it won't compile.
The compiler says, I
don't know what student is.
I don't know what courses,
What are you talking about?
And we say, oh, of course
we're going to include,
we better include student dot h because where
We're we're using the student type
and in particular we,
we are calling a member function on students.
So how would the compiler know
whether a student has
an enroll function or not?
If we don't include student that age.
And of course, because we're talking
about a pointer to a course,
we'll, we'll also include course dot h.
So we tried to compile this now.
Now of course we have include guards were
following the guidelines of
having Include Guard.
So student dot h has an Include Guard.
And the symbol we're using for
that astute included
course dot h has
an Include Guard, the symbol.
That is course included. Okay, so
let's try to compile this.
All right, so we're going to try to
include student dot age
that starts off by saying,
have we included this and you know,
have we defined the symbol yet?
No, we haven't. So we're
going to process all this text.
All right, so we'll define student
included will say Here's
what it means to be a student.
And the compiler barbs
when it sees the word course.
I don't know what a course is.
We say, oh yes, of course,
student dot h is
making use of the name course.
So we'd better, we'd
better include core studies.
So let's try this again.
We compile myapp dot cpp.
We, we include student dot age.
Student H starts off by saying,
have we been here before?
Now we haven't. So we'll
define the symbol student
included will go include
core stage before we go on.
Okay, So let's go include course dot h,
which says have we been here
before, know we haven't.
So let's define the symbol course
included and start processing.
Here's what a course is.
Ok, Whoops, we come to the named student.
We don't know what a student is.
What we have, we included student dot h.
Now we haven't
finished including student body.
Remember, we said include student dot h
and that started off
by including course dot h.
So we haven't yet gotten to
the declaration of the student type.
And now we run across the word stood.
So you say, Okay,
I guess that means coursed
on H on includes circled
student dot h. So let's try this again.
So we try to include student on each here in
my app dot cpp student dot h says,
have I been here before?
Know, so let's define
the symbol stood, include it.
And let's go include course dot h.
Course dot h says have we been here before?
Know, so let's define
the symbol course included.
And let's go includes student dot h.
And student dot h says,
have I been here before?
Well, yes, I have.
We've already defined the students circle.
We've already defined
the symbol student included.
Skip all this.
And therefore, we don't
process the declaration of the student type.
And we'll come back in here,
we continue on and we
still don't know what a student this,
so this isn't going to work.
This is a so-called circular dependency.
It's a circular dependency.
Student depends on course
and course depends on student.
So the problem comes
in trying to do this compilation.
We can't process the declaration of
student without knowing that course
is the name of a type.
And we can't process
the declaration of course,
without knowing the student
is the name of the type.
And so we've got this problem here.
And try as you may, if you're,
if student dot h is somehow going to
include course dot agents in course dot h is
somehow going to include student dot h.
You can't solve this nicely.
People try things like,
well maybe all not define the student
included symbol until after
I've included course dot h and blah,
blah, blah, and you try
various rearrangements of things.
Maybe I'll put something
outside the Include Guard.
Ooh, no, don't do that either.
A,
you try various rearrangements
and none of them.
You may solve this immediate problem.
But then some other situation
where a client is including
student dot h and course dot age or
one of them and it's not going to work right.
Or maybe we should first
include course dot h then student at it.
No, no, no.
So let me get to the solution.
First of all, let me note that C plus,
plus and C basically
allow you when you declare a class
and a struct or a structure to
provide a
so-called incomplete type declaration.
So if I define a class or
a structure this way,
this is an incomplete type declaration.
I'm announcing that a is the name of a type,
but I'm not saying any details about it.
That's what that semicolon saying is just,
I'm telling you is the name of the class,
but I'm not going to give you
any details right now.
Now later on in the compilation,
you could say, Oh,
by the way, here is
the full declaration of a.
In fact, in the same declaration,
you can have
as many incomplete type
specifications as you like.
Now nobody would write this this way,
but we'll see why this is, this is okay.
So compiling the same file, this is all fine.
You can have as many incomplete
type declarations as you like,
but no more than one actual full,
full-blown declaration
of the type of the class.
We'll see why that's why that's useful.
What's the purpose of this is to let
the compiler know that
a is the name of a type.
But we're not saying anything about a.
Well, we don't always
need to know details about a.
So let's go back to this and
see how that solves the problem.
Now, notice that when
we declare the student type,
student has a parameter that
is a pointer to a course,
and student has an array of course points.
Now there's a role in C plus plus that,
that when you declare a structure or a class,
the compiler needs to be able to
figure out the size of such an object.
So if I declare a student B
and tell you how it's
implemented with an array
of 10 course pointers.
The compiler has to know how
big the student is.
Now, an array of 10 objects
is going to be 10 times the size
of one of those things.
So an array of 10 study with 10,
an array of 10 course pointers is going to
be 10 times the size I've of course point.
How?
Because of course pointer.
Well, there's a rule in C plus, plus,
all pointers are the same size
and the compiler knows that size.
So if we're on a machine where pointers
are always four bytes long,
all pointers are four bytes long no matter
what they point to 0.
So do we need to know
any details about the course
tied to know that
this is a four-byte pointer.
Now, so the compiler says, oh,
okay, list is an array
of ten pointers to things.
And pointers are four bytes long,
so study list is 40 bytes long,
so I know how big this is, I'm happy.
So in other words, to,
to use a pointer to something,
the compiler only needs to know
that that's the name of a type course is
the name of the type doesn't need to
know any details about course.
So in particular, student dot h does
not need to include, whoops, course dotted.
All it needs is
to know course is the name of a type.
And we have broken the circular dependency.
We broken the fact that, well,
student dot h needs to include
course dot h and courts
dot h needs to include circled.
Anymore, student diets
doesn't include course dot h.
All student dot h has to
know is course is the name of a type.
And that's enough to process
these declarations using these pointers.
Now it also turns out,
in fact that course doesn't need to
know any details about student neither.
So we will go ahead
and use an incomplete
STI test specification here.
In general, if you can get away with
using an incomplete type specification,
do so.
If you can get away with
not including the header file and
simply providing
an incomplete type specification.
Do that. One of
the reasons is to break
circular dependencies,
but another reason is
that and it speeds up your compilation.
Enlarge systems.
You don't want to needlessly
include header files.
If you don't have to include a header file.
In a large system, you generally don't want
to do so because you,
it means to combine likes to go look at
that header and deal with stuff.
Now we don't care about multiple
including standard header file.
Standard headers are often
treated differently by the compiler.
And if you include the same
standard header file more
than once directly or
indirectly, that's harmless.
If you include a header, you
don't really need that.
That's, that's harmless.
A standard header that you don't need.
So including iostream, if you don't
really ever use it, that's harmless.
All right, so we've now solved the problem.
We broken the circular dependency.
In fact, we've broken
at both places, so that's fine.
I'm including student dot h says,
Okay, Have I been here before?
No, I haven't.
So let's, let's define the symbol.
O.
Course is the name of the type. Okay, Fine.
Thank you for telling me that.
Let's let's now see
what it is to be a student.
Oh, why know the name of course?
Course is the name of the type. Okay.
So CPS a pointer to a course.
Oh, I know what a course is.
Why don't know details,
but I know it's the name of the type.
So, oh, you're declaring an array of
ten pointers to courses. That's fine.
Okay, So that's fine.
We know is going to be 40.
So the compiler is happy.
And now we know what a student is.
Now when we include course dot h.
Have we seen this before?
It no.
So let's define the symbol
o students the name of a type.
Well, I've already seen
the complete declaration of student.
I already know that.
Is that a problem?
No, because as I said,
you can have
multiple incomplete types us vacation.
So so if we've already seen that student,
here's the full student declaration.
And now I'm going to tell
you students the name of a type.
That's harmless.
Okay?
And so we know students
the name of a type already anyway,
we process course, we see
the pointer to a student, that's fine.
We know what student is,
we know how big the roster is.
It's 1000 times the size of a pointer.
Okay, and when we're done with this,
we now know what a course is.
And so the rest of this is fine.
Now, in myapp dot cpp,
could I say class student,
and just leave it at that?
And class course and just leave it at that.
No.
No, I can't because this
won't compile because although okay,
we know students the name
of the type we're talking
about a pointer we know of
course is the name of a type.
We're talking about
a pointer that's harmless.
We are depending here on knowing
that student has
a member function called enroll.
And you don't know that from
this all I know student the name of a type.
I don't know anything about what
member functions it has.
So now we'd have to,
we'd have to fully include student dot h.
Now, for just this much,
we actually could get away
with saying class course,
because all we're saying is, hey,
this function takes in a pointer to
a course and passes
it on to the enroll function,
which wants a pointer to a course.
So does this code itself
need to know anything more about course,
what member functions it
has or how big it is now.
Now we don't actually need that.
So we could just get
away with saying class course.
But you know,
in a CPP file you're less persnickety about,
about don't include things
you don't really have to.
If you go ahead in the CPP file
and say include course
dot h. That's, that's okay.
Nobody's going, He's
going to yell at you for doing that.
Okay.
So that's the that's
the circular dependency issue
that I wanted to make sure
we were we were good on here.
And so when do
you when do you have to include
the header file and when can you get away
with simply
using an incomplete type specification?
And so here's, here's when you
can get away with just
using an incomplete type specification
instead of having to include
the whole federal header file.
The basic principle is if
the compiler needs to
know some details about the type,
then you'll have to include the header file.
If all it needs to know is it's the name of
a type you can get
away without, without that.
So when do we have to know the detail?
What does the Bible have to know
the details about a time?
Well, if you declare a data member,
That's of that time.
Not a pointer, not a reference.
Empty eclectic, Claire data member, That's,
that's of that type,
then the compiler has to know how big it is.
If you declare a container
of those actual objects.
So like an array of objects of that type,
then it has to now pointers now.
But, but an array, yes.
If you go ahead and
declare an object of that type,
it has to know
about that tie because I have to know what
Constructors constructors
are available for that type.
And if you use a member, you have to know.
So let's see here. If I have
a block class and I have
some data members that are,
here is a data member that is
an object of type foo.
So the compiler has to know how big it
is and to know how big a foo
is and has to see
the whole Declaration of food
and also whose data members are.
We have an array of 10 foo objects.
Same thing, we'd need to
know how big a foo is.
We, I'm talking about vectors yet
if we have a vector of foo,
it needs to know that it's a
collection of foo objects.
And so, and so we need that.
On the other hand, here we
only have pointers to F2s.
And since the compiler knows
how big a pointer is,
we can get away with just saying class foo.
We don't have to include the header file.
For just the prototype of a function,
you also can get away with saying class foo.
Well, certainly we know,
yeah, sure there's a pointer to a foo.
It's also true for a reference to a foo.
The compiler doesn't know
any details about the type.
And for a parameter of this type,
not a pointer, not a reference
but a parameter, the food type.
If all you're doing is having the prototype.
You don't need the full class declaration.
You say, well, wait a minute, passing
by value means copying.
Doesn't the compiler have to know how
big it is to copy it?
Not in the prototype.
In the prototype, we're not actually calling
the function and neither
are implementing the function and
needing to know how to
copy it, then how big it is.
It's just saying when you call this function,
you can go ahead and pass it
by value and that's okay.
Now, if we implement the function,
then yes, by implementing
the function that takes
an argument pass by value,
we got to include the header file,
declaring a local variable
of that type got to
include the header file because it
has to know how big this variable is.
If, if the food type has
some members like a Glebe function,
then the compiler has to know that
there is such a thing as a grep
function for the food types.
So we have to include the header file.
Okay, So that's a,
that's a summary of the rules.
Rules there. So here's
a question about circular dependencies.
When, if we're deciding,
you know, we gotta break circular dependency.
Well, what if we're
not dealing with pointers?
What if we're dealing with actual objects?
So let's see what that would look
like and why that is not a problem.
So let's say an object has a
biotic inside it and be
object as maybe an ENT number
and an a object inside.
So we have struct data
has a B object inside it struck BY,
that has an int and an a object inside.
Now, of course for this to compile,
we need the compiler has to see the name B.
So you say, Well, kinda do that.
No, that's, that's a data member
of type B, not a pointer to a B.
So I asked to see the whole Declaration 0.
Then I guess we got to
put the declaration of a,
of a, but we put
the full declaration to be up above a.
We have the same problem here.
So you can't solve the problem here.
You cannot have a contain a b object,
and B contain an object.
There's no way to order
those declarations to make it work and no,
using any complete text
specification will solve the problem.
But I'll say, Well,
but you wouldn't want to do this
anyway. You can't.
This would be illegal anyway,
even if the compiler did allow you somehow
to talk about before we saw the definition.
Because think about it.
What does an a object look like?
If I declare a variable a of type a,
a little lowercase a type a.
This object is an object layout there.
Now capital a object has
inside it just one data member,
which is NB object.
Now if the object has inside it integer am.
Object which hasn't side of the object,
which hasn't signed integer and an, a object.
And, and so it looks like we got some kind
of infinite problem here I am.
Here's a simple way to ask
how big is an a object?
So let's see.
The size of an a object.
Since it contains has to
be object is going to be
presumably the size of the B option, okay?
And the size of the object,
let's say integers or four bytes long is 4.
Plus the size may happen.
Okay?
So we can substitute
size of B and we find that
the size of an a object,
besides money object, is equal to
4 plus the size of an object.
So solve that equation.
How many bytes does AnyObject occupy?
Well, the solution to this
is basically
the only solution here is infinite.
If x is infinite, then
infinity is equal to 4k plus there.
So you'd have an infinite
size object that's not allowed.
All right, so this situation will not occur.
So now I want to go on to
our next major topic area,
which is resource management.
Now, what do I mean by resource?
A resource is something that the program
needs to use in order to do its job.
It's rather like the use of
the word resource in economics.
A resource is something that a person or
a company or a society wants or needs.
Things like food or oil
or money or land, or labor.
In any event, if a resource is unlimited,
there's no need to manage it.
In a computer context.
For example, if we have
an infinite amount of memory
available, we always have as much.
Or even if not literally,
infant will always have
enough memory as much as we might need.
You could write programs, I
could be very efficiently
solved if you had
an array with a gazillion elements,
if you had all that space of L,
you might be able to do things
more efficiently than if
you had to run with some limitations.
So in the case of
unlimited resources is not interesting.
There's nothing demand,
there's no need to manage.
We're looking at the issues
involving limited resources,
things like memory.
There's only so much memory
or our processor time.
If you're on a computer system with
one processor that can execute
instructions at a certain rate,
that's kind of a limitation.
And if there's a lot
of computation that you want to get done
or you have
multiple programs that are running
simultaneously and
there's only one processor,
how do you allocate the time of the processor
from between all the programs.
So there's a limitation,
limitations on how much disk space you have,
limitations on how many files
your program might have
open at the same time.
You have limitations on
how many network connections you might have.
At the same time, the operating system will
put limits on limits like these.
So the, the issue of management then is,
is you've gotta be aware of these issues.
You've gotta be aware of these limitations
and write your programs in
a way that don't ignore
those issues because they will
come up and bite you at some point.
At some point you'll,
you'll run into a problem.
So for example, maybe I have a program
that is going to process 1000 files.
And what my program's going to
do is work like this.
It's going to open a file.
What brands yourself. So I'm going to open
a file, process it,
then I'm going to open the next file,
process it, and then open
the next file, process it, et cetera.
That's my algorithm.
Now the problem is if
my operating system as a limit
on how many open files
I can have in my program at a time.
Let's say it's 128.
Usually pick some power to, let's say,
and let's say it's a 100,
There's a limited let's say there's
a little bit of a 100 open files I can have.
Well, what's going to happen
is if I open a file,
use it, open a file,
use it, open a file, use it.
After I've opened a 100 files.
When I open a 100 file number a 100 one,
the open I'll fake am and so I got a problem.
So usually if there's
some kind of resource and
a way to acquire that resource.
In the case of files,
opening the file is,
among other things, acquiring, you know,
the the the open file descriptor information,
et cetera, for that file,
if there's only a finite amount of that,
there needs to be a one, needs
to be a way to release the resources,
give it back to the operating system.
So you can open a file.
You can close the file.
When you close a file,
it's no longer open that releases
the resource that
the operating system is holding for the five.
So a correct implementation would be,
would be if, if once,
if once I process to file,
I don't have to look at it again.
Correct implementation would simply
be opened a file,
use it, close the file,
open a file, use it.
Close the file, open a file, use it closer.
By that way.
I have at most one file
open at any given time.
So I'm not going to run out, I'm not
gonna hit my 100 file limit.
I can go ahead and process
a 1000 files, 10 thousand files,
because I'm never going to
have more than one file open at a time,
so I never come close to that 100 file
it on an open file descriptors.
So there's an example of a writing code
that manages the resource
of open files correctly.
So there's lots and lots of resources you,
one another one would be,
say, exclusive access to a database record.
So you'll have a situation,
for example, where I have a bank account,
let's say it has a $100 in
and say two people share the same account.
They both have ATM cards.
They both go up to an ATM machine
at two different our
ATM machines and into parts of the city.
Let's say they both
take their cards in it about the same time.
They both asked to withdraw a $100.
Okay?
So one thing that
might happen is the way the ATM machine
works as it does the following.
Oh, you want to withdraw a 100 adults?
So what I'm gonna do, go check,
go get your your current balance,
check it to make sure you have
enough to withdraw that amount.
If so, then I will dispense you the cache.
I will subtract that amount from your
balanced and store it back in the database.
And so you can see there's a problem here.
If this machine says,
let me get the balance which is a $100.
Okay?
You want a $100, that's fine.
So I'm going to dispense
the cache and I'm going to subtract a
100 from this before it
gets a chance to write back
to 0 because your balance is now empty.
The other one says,
you know, starts ovens and says, Oh,
I'm going to get the balance which
is still a 100 up here,
the database, I'll get the 100,
you know, you've got it and you want a $100.
Final, give it to you,
I'll set the thing desert.
Meanwhile, this guy gets
around to writing back to
0 and this guy gets
rendered writing back Zara,
and both of you got a $100 and
the account balance is now 0
and you wind bank loses.
So, so there's gotta be
some kind of exclusive access.
Typically that's going to be some kind of
idea of a lock that you have to
acquire a lock and release the lock
so that the right transaction is 0.
I'm going to be working math and I kept,
let me acquire a lock on that account,
which means the database will say,
if somebody's got the lock,
I'm not going to let anybody else lock
this account yet or access anything on.
So if I say I'm going OK in the record,
the database says nobody's
got the lock in that record. Okay.
You've got the lock.
I will not let anybody
else acquire
the lock for this this right. Okay.
So fine.
I've got the lock so I can get the balance.
I do my thing while I'm
in the middle of doing this thing.
This guy says, You know,
I'd like to try to get that record.
Davis says, Well, you gotta lock first.
I'm sorry.
I would like to acquire the lock.
The database says, Well, you got to wait,
cuz somebody else has the law.
So this guy has to wait.
Once this guy has taken up a $100,
written back a 0 balance,
it then says, Okay, I'm
done, release the lock.
So the database says fine,
now you've got your lock.
So so it kept this process
from doing stuff with
the record until this one did.
So this idea of acquiring
and releasing locks,
there's only a finite number of blocks you
can have the submissions involved with that.
There's another example
of resources to manage.
So in our case, the,
the resource we're going to manage in
this class that comes up
over and over again is memory.
So your machine has
only a finite amount of memory to give you.
And you want to
write applications that don't
run out of memory.
So let me, let me go
through the setup
for how this is going to work.
So let's say that.
Let's say I'd like to do,
is I guess the easiest way
to do this is to, because so many,
so many aspects of memory manager, Art,
mentor about memory management
are already handled by the library.
Let me go back to
before there was a library doing it for you.
So let's go back in time, about 30 years.
So we're back in 990.
There is no C plus plus Standard.
Different compiler writers have
slightly different interpretations of
what some of the things in C plus plus mean.
In particular, there's no standard library.
There's no standard string type.
Every compiler vendor is writing
their own string type for you to
use, to use their library.
They're all slightly different.
So here we are, where we're going to provide
a string type for
people who aren't using our compiler to use.
So we're going to write
a string type and there
is no standard C plus plus string type.
So that's the environment
this example's going to be.
Now, we do of course,
have the C standard library.
Which has standard functions
for manipulating C strings.
So STR see PY string copy to
copy a C string and an array
of characters with 0 byte at the end.
Strlen to figure out the length of
a C string that, that exists.
But we're going to have to
write our own string type.
So let me start the setup,
and that would be how
we might want to use our string type.
So as a simple example usage,
I want to have some function h.
And it creates a string,
say with the text
Hello and does stuff with it.
So in order for that much to work,
will want to have a string plus I'll use
a capital S to distinguish it
from the library type string,
which we're assuming doesn't exist yet.
For that to work, we
need to have a constructor for string.
And it's going to take as its argument,
basically a C string at
a double quoted string literal in C and
C plus plus represents
an array of characters.
In fact, an array of constant characters,
array of characters you promise not to
modify an array of
characters with
a 0 byte terminating that string.
So what that means is somewhere in memory,
there's an array the compiler has laid
out with a capital H, lowercase,
a lowercase, a lowercase l,
a lower-case 00 byte, somewhere in memory.
There's this array the compiler
has set up for us.
It does that anytime you write
a string literal, okay,
so in an expression
where you use a string literal like that,
the compiler is going to say, okay,
I need to pass this array
to a constructor function.
Now of course, you can't pass on
our ray by value to a function.
And we learn that C and CS 31, when you,
when you think you're
passing an array to a function,
you're really passing a pointer
to element 0 of the array.
So this string constructed
is really receiving is
the pointer to the first of many characters.
And the expectation
is it's going to be a C string,
so it ends with a 0 bytes.
So there's my constructor.
So the, as I said,
the next thing to think about
is if this is what we want to have,
we should be thinking about.
Is there any other functionality
we want to have?
And then we can
start thinking about representation.
So let me think about this.
Are there other ways I
want to create a string?
In particular, do I
want to have a default constructor?
And you'd almost surely say, sure,
there's a reasonable default value
for strings, the empty string.
So why do we allow
a default constructor as well?
Okay,
so then what we're
going to start thinking is,
all right, Then let's
start thinking about representations.
So, well, Here's a real simple one.
Why don't we just have an array of
characters and the object.
So every spring object simply has
this one data member that's
an array of a 100 character.
Well, there's some problems with this.
In particular, the main problem
is if you have an array,
then the number of elements in the array,
if you're declaring an array,
the number of elements in
the array has to be a constant
known at compile time.
We have to pick some constant to put there.
I picked a 100.
What's not so great about that?
Well, what if I
want to have strings that are
more than a 100 characters?
I won't be able to fit long strings in here.
So, oh, okay, Well,
surely nobody wants a string of
say, a 100 thousand characters.
So let's put that there then.
That'll be room for any string,
room enough for any spring somebody wants.
What's wrong with that?
Well, then the problem is
every string is going to
take up a 100 thousand bytes.
Even a string like hello where we only
really need five
and we're going to be using a 100.
That's a lot of wasted space.
You won't be able to have too many strings in
your program without running out of memory.
So the problem with a fixed number
is if it's too big,
you're wasting a lot of space and might
not be able to have a lot of these
are objects of this type.
And if it's too small,
there'll be a lot of
things that we can't represent.
A lot of strength we can't
represent because it's too
short so that I have to reject that.
So the only other alternative is to say,
Well then let's instead make the texted,
the string dynamically allocated and
our object will hold a pointer
to the text of the string.
We'll try something like that.
So the idea would be then
a string object like ask
will have one data member,
the M text data member.
And we'll, we'll have it be a pointer to
a dynamically allocated array of characters.
Possibly.
Why not just have it be a copy of the season?
So we'll dynamically allocate
an array of characters big
enough to hold the string and then
will store a pointer to it.
Well, of course, as soon as you start
working with dynamic allocation,
you're saying, hey, operating system,
give me some storage for, for this array.
Well, there's
only a finite amount of storage,
so that's a resource that has to be managed.
We have to make sure that we don't use
up all the storage for strings.
We don't even need the memory for anymore.
So working all that out is going to be
the topic of what issues come up.
The problem is, resource management
is not a trivial issue.
It starts off looking that way.
It's like, oh, sure,
for any resource we allocate,
we gotta give it
back when we're done with it,
there's more and there's
many ways to go wrong.
And so that's what we got to see later.
I also wanted to default constructor,
which will produce the empty string.
Whoops, I spilled coffee on my shirt.
Oh no. Let me change my shirt.
Hang on.
Okay.
Where was I?
If I also want to default constructor,
which would produce an empty string.
And that leads me to think
about the representation.
How can I represent an empty string?
So I can see
two possibilities that would be reasonable.
One would be, well,
this is what a string of
five interesting characters looks like.
A six element array with
five interesting characters
followed by a 0 byte.
Then a two character string would have
two interesting characters followed by us
or by an empty string.
What I have now, interesting characters
followed by a 0 by.
So one way to represent
the empty string would be,
how about have a dynamically
allocated array of one byte.
And, and we're going to put the 0 byte there.
That'll be our representation
of the empty string.
That'll work.
But there's another possibility.
How about just a point?
So that would also conceivably
be a reasonable representation
of the empty string.
So before we go any further,
we probably should make a decision,
or at least a tentative decision.
And then as we implement,
we may decide, Oh,
that wasn't the right decision
we wanted to make us make
the other decision because
both of these are perfectly reasonable.
I mean, here's the arguments for both cases.
The first case, I
went with this representation
for the empty string,
it's consistent with
every other non-empty string.
So, so that would probably
make our implementation code.
Easier because it's not a special case.
The empty string would just another string.
It's not as if we're guaranteed
every string has a non null pointer here.
It points to in
a dynamically allocated array.
It's got the text to
the characters that make up
the strand followed by a 0 back by,
that would be uniform across all strings.
And that would make our job
as an implementer easier.
On the other hand, the empty string
is a very frequently occurring string.
If I decide to declare an array
of a 100 thousand strings,
each string will be
constructed whenever you create
an array of objects of a class type,
every element will be default constructed.
So that'll be a 100 thousand
default constructor, empty strings.
Now, to dynamically allocate storage,
whether it's a bigger a or a small array,
takes dozens of instructions.
Does the machine language instructions
to dynamically allocate storage,
even if it's just a one byte array.
So the cost of
creating an array of
a lot of empty strings is
going to be lots and lots of instruction is
getting executed to properly
build those empty strengths.
And when we go away,
the destructor gets called on each of
those strings and that takes
several dozen instructions.
So there's a time cost
with this representation of the empty string.
There's also a space cost
and it's more than you might think.
It looks like every empty string
is going to take up one byte.
And in fact, when you
dynamically allocate storage,
there has to be some bookkeeping information
that the storage allocator keeps.
It keeps around to keep track of, you know,
how big that dynamically allocated storage
is because when you call
it delete to get rid of it,
when you use delete to get rid of
it dynamically allocated item,
all you give delete is where it is.
So somehow the storage allocator have to have
some bookkeeping information to figure out
how much space do we get
back to the operating system.
So so that overhead,
that extra space overhead
for the bookkeeping information,
that could be eight bytes, maybe more.
So our array of
a 100 thousand empty two strings
is not only going to take up
space for the strings themselves,
which each string is
just takes up the size of a pointer,
but also the dynamically allocate
an array and the bookkeeping information.
And so the overhead is, well,
if it's eight bytes per object,
and we have a 100 thousand strings in our,
in our array, that's 800 kilobytes,
just a bookkeeping information
for those empty strengths.
On the other hand, if the empty string is
represented as this way
with the null pointer in here,
there is no extra storage overhead.
So that safe space and
the cost to initialize
this to be to the null pointer,
you know,
one machine language instruction essentially.
So, so if I
were designing this for practical purposes,
I would probably want to have
the empty string be
a special case represented this way.
Now that's going to make all my
implementation's a little
more complicated for me,
the developer implementing string,
because I have to check for that case,
every other string is
a non null pointer here,
but the empty string would have a null point.
That would make my code and let me know.
And people pay more attention
when writing the code to implement
the member functions of strengths
for users don't care about us.
They just use the string type.
It works from their point of view.
But
And implemented,
I would have to do more work.
So the choices between
doing more work for me, the implementer,
in order to make my user's life easier,
taking up less storage,
faster performance, et cetera.
Or make my life as an implementer easier.
But it's going to be a little more
costly for users to use my strengths.
So this is kind of
from the second Star Trek movie,
the needs of the many outweigh
the needs of the few or the one,
the needs of all my users,
making life easier for all my users.
So my stream type is more important
than saving me a little bit of extra work.
So this would be the right decision to make.
And in fact, if you look
at most library implementations,
the string type and standard library,
you find that indeed they'll have
a simpler representation for
the empty string that,
that doesn't need to allocate
storage because that saves time.
This is better for everybody.
Now, that said,
that's the decision I would make
it in the real world in
practice for our purposes,
for this explanation of going
through the resource management issue.
That's just an extra complication
I we would have.
So I'm going to make the decision
that for this presentation,
representation of the empty string
will look like that.
So it'll be a dynamically allocated array
with Zuora by them.
So there you go.
I've decided on my representation for string,
but, but wait a minute.
I will discover as I
implement many member functions for strings,
useful things to do with
strings that may have
those functions need to
find out the length of the string.
So many of my member
functions for string will,
as part of their work, need
to know the length of the string.
So notice that the only way
this representation to know the length
of the string is to
start from the pointer and find the 0 line,
which is what the strlen function does.
Remember on my assumption that this
is 990 and we don't
have a standard library with
the B glass from seeing what class,
we still have
the C standard library available.
So we can use functions for
C strings like strlen.
So anytime, anywhere, any of
our other functions need to
know the length of the string,
they've got a visit every bite of the string.
So for a long string that
could be, that could be costly.
So here's another thought
for how I represent a string.
I'll store not only a pointer to the tax,
but also how many
interesting characters are in the string.
So every string object will have two members.
If I make this decision,
one will be a pointer to the, the,
the text and one will be what the,
the, the length of that text is.
So five interesting characters
here is 0 interesting characters here.
I'll do that because I think that'll make
my implementations takes them
a little more space for string object,
but, but it makes
the implementation is faster.
I think anytime you think this is going to
be the better choice for
various performance region reasons,
you would want to measure that.
So, so again, in real-world situations,
you make your decision,
you run some tests, you measure it.
You maybe consider the alternating
implementation, run some tests,
measure it and see
which one is in fact going to,
going to be better for you.
So, to make our presentation easier,
this is the choice I'll make.
That leads me to going back to code bell,
easy to say, okay, I will
have an additional data member.
That'll,
that'll hold the length of the string.
All right, So again,
it's a good idea to document
your class invariant if
you make these decisions.
So I'll say that.
All right, So my class invariant,
invariant properties of my representations,
so I keep track and make sure
I always satisfy them.
One of them is of course,
that mtext is a pointer to my intent.
It's a dynamically allocated array.
And how many characters in the array?
Well, actually it should
be related to the M1,
enough characters to hold
the interesting characters in
the string plus one more for
this terabyte at the end, of course.
Another property is the length
of a string has to be at least 0.
And another property is
that there is a 0 byte at the end.
Well actually here's another way to
say M line is supposed to
represent the result of what
calling strlen would give me.
So, so if I call the C library
function strlen on M text,
I should get back the length.
So I've decided what
my data representations are.
Now I can start implementing the functions.
So I will implement my constructor.
And let me, let me try this implementation.
Well, that's a C string,
so I'll sign it there.
So I try something like that as
my, as my implementation.
This is wrong.
This is an incorrect implementation.
This is wrong because
It's going to lead to some funny effects.
So let's see what
those funny effects would be.
Alright, so again, remember
the constructor is
simply taking the parameter,
you give it the pointer and
stuffing it in the M text.
And also taking the length of that,
that stuck and sticking in the mLab.
So let me, let me
take a look at what that would do.
Absolutely get an example where
the positive character array,
okay, I found an array of characters pop.
All right, I will,
I'll read a line of input.
Now, admittedly, and 990,
the standard library wasn't standardized,
but many, many libraries
had implementations where okay too,
I see, or you could call getline are.
And you get the array limit
on how many characters to store.
So that will read a line of input,
Let's say the user types in hello.
So the user types in hello,
and this is going to put it in
this character array with his thereby.
Okay, so again, hello to 0 byte at the end.
Now let's create a string
object from that string.
Okay, Now as I,
as I wrote the constructor,
my constructor said, okay,
we have our two numbers, our texts and MLN.
And as I wrote the constructor,
I said m texts gets the argument if I'm
passing a pointer to buffer
because an array name by assault
and disappointed at element 0,
the array, if I pass that
as to the constructor as value.
And if my constructor
says assign value to m tax,
well then that pointer gets assigned M text
and strlen and value becomes
m land was the other code I said.
And we leave the constructor,
the local parameter
value because the right way,
and here it is as has
a pointer to hello with a 0,
but at the end, and Atlanta's
five looks great.
Did all kinds of stuff I can do with that.
That'll be right.
So look like it has the text,
Hello, everything, everything seems legit.
There's only one problem.
It's very confusing to the user for.
Well, if the user later on,
say reads another line
and put it into the buffer,
figuring that, okay, I can align it input,
I typed it below that,
got put into the strengths,
so the strings got the **** out.
Nevertheless, let me go use
the buffers for something else.
So I read a line of input to the buffer.
Let's say that line of input is, Oh,
wow, well, buffers right here.
So incomes, the wildlife being out alone,
actually pillow occupy six characters here.
If I 3D and wow,
will get the w o to w 0
by leftover from the halo would be
the final lower-case 00 byte here.
Basically, we are putting WOW, 0 right here.
And now we've got
the strange situation, right?
We ready and to buffer,
we made no mention of the string s.
Yet this change, conceptually what S is value
is now code that uses
AES and tries to do
stuff with the string is going to get,
well, it's gotta be weird because
the code is going to think that
the length of the string is five.
And well, it's not.
The strlen is,
there's really only up to here,
so it's only really effectively three.
The string value changed out from under us.
It, it, it was hello before and
now Ss values no longer hello,
but we didn't even mention us.
This is totally wrong.
This is, this is really bad,
bad practice here because our expectation
is that if I create a string from that tax,
that tax no longer matters.
If now belongs to the strength.
Well, that's not what we did.
We saved a pointer to
where that text came from M.
And that's well, okay.
So what we want is when you create a string,
each string gets its own array of text.
Let me go back to the code here.
Now, actually,
there's another reason this is wrong.
It won't even compile.
Value is a pointer to constant characters.
M text says is
declared as a pointer to texts.
That is, we don't promise not to modify.
Compiler won't even let you do that.
So, so this won't even compile.
But if you thought, well,
why don't I make this not a
pointer to constant characters less promised.
Let's not promised not to
modify the characters.
Get rid of the const here,
and then we can go ahead and do this.
Well, yeah,
that assignment would then be, would compile.
But we still have this weird problem that
the strings value changes out from under it.
So now, now, and in fact,
I already anticipated that in
my class and barium and I said,
Wait a minute, am tax is a pointer
to a dynamically allocated array.
Well, no, it's not, not here.
So yeah, I totally messed up here.
So now let's, let's do this right.
Now. What we did for M line is correct.
I'm text needs to be
a dynamically allocated array
of some number of characters.
That's what we need to set.
Dynamically allocated an array
of the appropriate number of characters.
New will give us back
a pointer to the beginning of that array.
And that's what gets stored at M text
and how many characters?
Well, big enough to hold the string.
But since I decided I want my representation
of the string to have a 0 byte at the end.
It's not going to be m land,
it's going to be m land plus one.
So that causes the string to,
right now the contents out though,
instead of going to live to
the white board or put it here,
the contents of the strings M text,
okay, It's, it's, it's
M line is going to be five.
And the M text right now is going to be
an array of, at the very moment, it
Uninitialized character,
we dynamically allocate
an array of six characters.
We didn't yet say what values they have.
So we need to make sure we take
the text of the string here.
Value is a pointer to that to be
hello string them that's empty.
And let us five and we have
the array of 600 initialized characters.
We need to get those characters into mtext.
Again, we have the C standard library
so we can use string copy.
So we will copy into M text from value.
So again, str copy
takes two pointers to characters.
The first is a pointer to carry
an array of characters you can modify.
The second is he's appointed
to characters and, and,
and the function is not going to
modify those characters.
And so it'll copy the characters
from the second array into the first array,
stopping after it copies a 0 byte.
So if value is pointing to the hello string,
this, this constant string
in memory that has hello.
Then we're gonna get our h here,
or here, or here,
or I guess I missed one question marks
and is thereby the character who's,
who's representation is 0.
Okay, so now S looks like that.
If we passed it hello,
does that satisfy our invariant?
Mtext is a pointer to
a dynamically allocated array of
five plus 16 characters.
Yes, we allocated six characters.
Five is greater than equal to 05
is indeed equal to strlen of M text.
All right, So there is
a correct implementation of
our constructor that takes one Arctic,
alright,
our constructor that takes no arguments,
the default constructor that we declared,
if that's our string t here.
So our string t, Let's see.
What we want t to look like
is, well, the M line should be 0.
So I guess we could that.
I decided I do want to go with
the representation where M text
is an array of
dynamically allocated characters.
So it'll be one character
and we want that to be the 0 byte.
So we can say that we
dynamically allocate an array of
one character and then
we set that to the 0 byte.
So that would be our representation
of the, the empty string.
Now be, before I go further,
I may decide that what I
want to do is examine
these two constructors and take
a look at their implementations.
And it's a worthwhile exercise.
You may end up, it may end up proving,
proving not so valuable,
but it's worth doing.
It's a worthwhile exercise to look at.
These two functions have
different parameter lists,
but this one is,
is shorter than that one.
There's a possibility of combination
here or something or, or,
or just look for commonality
in the implementations.
And maybe we might be able to factor that,
that commonality into
a common helper function or something.
So as an exercise,
what I'm going to try to do is,
for example, here's the general case
and here the empty string.
I'm going to try to
massage this code and try to make
this code look more
like be constructed
through with one argument code.
So let's see.
Well, this one says M texts gets
a new array of
characters of length m length plus one.
This one also says M text
gets a new array of characters,
but we just put one here.
But wait a minute,
could I make this look more like that?
Well, sure.
Mln is 00 plus one is, is one.
So I could say MLN
plus one here and that would still be one.
All right, Well that makes
that statement look more like
the other one. How about this one?
This one sets M.
Linda strlen of value.
This one says Sam, lend to 0.
Could I put like strlen
of something and have the answer be 0?
Is there something I
can replace the dot, dot,
dot with that will cause
strlen to return 0 because that
would then make this produce
the right result of 0 for M line, the M line.
But it looks more like the other constructor,
which is my, my goal for now.
To see if I can make these look more
similar to maybe factor out commonality.
While you think about it for
a bit and you say, Well,
the empty string has a length of zeros.
So if I put a double quote,
double quote for the empty string,
that, that would do the trick.
Okay, well, that's possibly interesting.
Now how about this last thing?
Here? I want to make sure that
the array contains a 0 byte in position 0.
Here I did a string copy to make
my array have the text of
the string with a 0 byte at the end.
Well, let's try this.
Could I do what's called a string
copy into em tags just like the other,
the other one with something or
another would end up having M text.
Look like that.
Just a 0 byte it,
is there anything I can copy into
N M text to do that?
And I think about it and say, well,
you know, if you copy the empty string,
the empty string is,
the empty string is going to
be just one character in it with a 0 byte.
And if I copy that see spring into
m tax than M text looks like that.
So the results of
this exercise is that
here's another implementation of
the default constructor that
looks just like the other constructor,
except with value being the empty string.
Well, if that's the case,
then I can do things the following way.
I can say, You know what,
I will just get rid
of this default constructor
and provide a default value to use if the,
if the color of the constructor
for string leaves off the argument.
If you leave off the argument,
act like the arguments,
the empty string, the double quote,
double quote, and then I don't even need
to declare this constructor at all.
So second I really work well.
Yeah.
So if I declares T This
way, the compiler says,
Okay,
it looks like you're trying to construct
a string and you're not
passing any arguments to the constructor.
Is there a constructor
that can take no arguments?
Well, I didn't declare
one that takes no arguments,
but I did declare one that
takes one argument and you're
allowed to leave it off and
the compiler will supply that argument o.
So the compiler says, Sure,
I will act as if you had said create
t and constructed it from the empty string.
So the compiler will
turn in the statement into,
into this one essentially a call to
the constructor with one argument
passing it the empty string.
So the compiler says, Okay, fine,
then I'll
execute this constructor where value
is a pointer to
an array of one character
that has a 0 byte in it.
Strlen of that is 0.
So, So t will get 0 for the NLN.
Dynamically allocate
an array of one character,
store a pointer to that an M text,
and copy the empty string into M text.
Okay, and so it does, and it works.
I get t looking like that.
What I want.
So you can't always do that.
Where does that result isn't
always going to end up being, Hey,
if I had those two functions
that were very similar and
I massage one of them
to look more like the other one.
Maybe I could actually combine them into one.
Doesn't always work.
This case, it worked out just fine.
Okay, so we simplified our implementation
by having that only one function
to maintain not more than one.
Alright, so let's see.
Any other things I want to do with this?
Well, I do want to think about, well,
anytime you pass a pointer to a function,
you should ask yourself,
what if somebody passes a null pointer?
That's always possibility.
They're not supposed to necessarily,
but think about what to do about that.
If somebody decides to create a string.
So let me go back up here.
Maybe they have a character pointer p,
and they do some stuff with P. And
ultimately they're then going to
create a string with P as an argument.
So there's some code that sets P somehow.
And then eventually we decided to say, OK,
now let's take the C string that p points
to and, and passed here.
Now, maybe setting P involve calling
some function that returns a pointer to
character that was supposed to
point to a C string.
And if the function couldn't do its job,
it returned a null pointer.
So it's possible maybe
that P has the null pointer value.
If P is a null pointer value,
then if we call this constructor this way,
in the environment of the constructor,
value is going to be the null pointer.
And our code starts off by saying, okay,
so let's see, let's
see what happens when we're constructing.
You, want to be constructing you.
So let's see what happens.
Values, the null pointer value got passed in.
We call strlen with the null pointer value.
So the answer for what happens now is
what does the C library do
if you pass strlen a null pointer.
And the C standard
and the C Plus Plus standard
agree that that's undefined behavior.
The strlen function is not obligated to,
to check for the null pointer and do
something reasonable that case
it could crash.
In fact, on most implementations that crash.
Okay, So we can't just do this,
we'll have to check for this ourself
to, for better safety.
So we will say, okay,
if value is in fact
the null pointer,
we're going to have to do something.
So again, now we
come up with a policy decision.
What should we do if the user
gives our string and null pointer?
Should we say that that's no good.
We're not gonna let you do that
or let's think about it.
If you're a client who passed
a null pointer to the string constructor,
knowing that
you're supposed to pass a pointer to
some C string plus
maximum C string like hello,
or even the empty string.
In fact, if you don't pass
any arguments at all,
you get the empty string.
I could think it's reasonable to
assume the null pointer
should probably produce an empty string two.
I think that would make sense that if I
constructed a string and I gave,
I gave an empty string as
the argument to the constructor.
I would expect that if this works,
it gives me the empty string.
Okay, I think that's reasonable.
So let me do that.
Let me make it so that if you pass
the null pointer to the string constructor,
you're going to get the empty string.
Now, the easiest way to do
that is rather than
kind of duplicate this code again,
let's just say, alright,
the parameter passed to
the function value is a local variable.
And that local variable value
starts off with a value of the null pointer.
Well, let's just make that local variable
now point to the empty string.
So we can just do that and then proceed.
So let's see what that's going to do.
Double quote, double quote.
As a C string constant, double quote,
double quote causes the compiler
to up in memory somewhere
an array of one character with
a 0 byte it and returns,
in this expression returns
a pointer to that,
the beginning of that array.
So the double quote,
double quote here in
this statement is going to be
a pointer to array characters
that we promised not to modify.
And we want to store that into value.
Can hold a pointer to
character as we promised not to modify.
Oh, okay, So now
value contains a pointer to us,
an array that has 0 byte,
which is perfect because now
strlen of that IT value is,
let me note that this is, it's pointing
to not a, not a carrier,
so that it's pointing to
an array of no character at one character,
an element 0 that arrays to 0 byte.
So, so let's call strlen on that,
that, that pointer to that array, okay,
Sterling gives us back 0 and
everything proceeds as we want and we
end up with you being
the M text is an array pointer
to an array that has, it's just a 0.
Byte, length is 0, so everything works out.
Okay? There we go.
We bullet-proof this.
So now no matter what you pass that,
we can check for whether you
pass a pointer to
a C string or you pass a null pointer,
we're, we're covered
and we do something reasonable.
What the function can't detect is,
well, what if you pass a pointer
to an array of characters?
But that array does
not contain a 0 byte in it,
so it's not a valid C string.
Well, there's no way
our function can know that.
Our function only gets
a pointer to where the array starts.
It has no idea how many characters make
up the actual declared size
of the array versus, versus.
Going beyond the end of
the array that it can't tell.
It.
It just says I, all I can
know is go until I see a 0.
All right,
sometimes people see things like this.
Say Wait a minute,
didn't you say value is const,
how can you assign to it?
Well, I'm not saying value is,
value is a local variable
of this, of this constructor.
It can change its value.
The type of the variable is
a pointer to constant characters.
The cost modifies the character.
The const says that
that value is a point you to characters,
and those characters cannot be modified.
If you try to go through the name value,
you won't be allowed
to modify those characters.
But you can certainly make
value point to a different array of
characters that can't be modified or
yet another array of
characters that can't be modified.
So value can point to
two different arrays over its lifetime.
It's just the through the name value.
You can't modify those characters.
Okay, so we end up with that.
That's our implementation of the constructor.
And we say, Okay, fine,
I guess this code is good.
And of course, no,
this code is not good
because if that's all we've got here,
we've got memory leaks.
So the problem is
that if we call the function h,
we're setting up three strings.
So let me stop sharing here.
And sorry, I have a function h
recreate a string hello.
We expect that one's
good enough to illustrate the problem.
We call the function h.
When h creates a string S,
that constructor is going to dynamically
allocate an array.
Similarly, by copy.
Hello.
Into the array, great.
We use S in the function.
When we leave the function,
as we had declared our string class,
when we leave the function,
local variables go away.
But S is this object here.
That's all that S is,
S is this object.
And we did not
declare a destructor for the string type.
So if you don't declare a destructor
for the string type, the compiler right?
One for you.
And if all the data members
are simply a built-in type,
the compiler generated destructor
does nothing interesting.
So it just says, okay,
the instructor finishes and now
the string object goes away,
but the dynamically allocated
array was never released.
You allocate something with new,
that storage belongs to
your program until you
call delete and pass
that a pointer to that storage.
So we have a memory leak
here every time we call h.
When it returns, there's
some storage allocated
that belongs to our program,
but we can't get to anymore
because we have no more pointers to.
And of course, the problem with memory leaks
is, is over time,
if you keep acquiring
more and more storage that you can't use.
Eventually some, at some point your program
runs up and they ask
for storage from the operating system.
The operating system says,
I don't have any more storage giving sorry,
and your program crashes
because it doesn't have enough memory,
even though logically it should,
because every time we're
done with the string,
we don't need the storage anymore,
but we didn't explicitly
use delete to give it back.
So that's the purposes of the destructor.
The purpose of a destructor,
the destructor for a class is to
release any resources that the object
called that's going away folds
so that they could potentially be re-used.
So it motivates you to write
a destructor is almost invariably
your objects over
its lifetime acquire some resource.
In our case, it was dynamic memory for this,
it acquires some resource
and you want to make sure
when the object goes away,
the resources released.
That's why you write destructors.
And so let me note the behavior destructors.
Now, I said we have here that the way
construction works
is whenever you have a constructor,
the compiler or
the constructor goes through three steps.
Step one isn't relevant to us yet.
Step 2 is construct the data members.
And we said how to do that.
Step 3 is due the body, the constructor.
Oh, by the way, I wrote
my constructor here and I didn't mention,
I didn't use
the memory initialization list to
initialize M line and M
text there built-in types,
they would be left on initialized
by step to a construction.
And instead I, I gave them their values.
And step 3 of construction,
partly because these are
slightly more complicated expressions.
I'm not just setting MLN to a simple value.
It's going to be the result
of calling strlen.
But I don't want to call strlen until after.
I know that values, not the null pointer.
And I don't want to initialize
M text until I've,
I've figured out m land.
And so to try to do that in
the membrane initialization list
makes it get pretty ugly.
The member initialization list
would have to arrange to
initialize m LAN using
some expression that will,
that will either be 0 if values
a null pointer or strlen a value of it's not.
And that gets more complicated and ugly.
So.
In this case, I chose not to use
the member initialization list to
initialize the data members
here because they're excuse.
There are some complicated stuff
that had to happen.
Anyway.
How does destruction work?
Well, the destructor also
goes through three steps,
and it's essentially kind
of the opposite of
construction in reverse order.
You do what the constructor does in
the opposite order and
you destroy instead of create.
So the first thing that
happens when a destructor gets
executed is the body
of the destructor gets executed,
then each data member is somehow destroyed.
What does that look like? Well, if
it's a built-in type, do nothing.
So if a data member as an int or a double,
a pointer or anything of a built-in type.
Nothing happens if it's
a class type that it'll
call that classes destructor,
okay, and then step 3 corresponds to step 1,
which we don't know anything about it.
So fill that in later.
Okay, since I did not
write a destructor for string,
the compiler rights and for
me that has an empty body.
So the way my strings get destroyed,
as I said, is not very good.
We do nothing for the body, the distracter.
And the two data member types
are built-in types,
character star, and ends.
So to start this step
2 does nothing for them.
And so we're left where?
Okay, now the string goes away,
but the dynamic storage for
the text to the string, It's still there.
So we gotta write a destructor for
the string type to clean that up.
So my string class will
have an instructor that I'll declare
and I will implement it.
Now the job of the destructor is to
leave the object in a state
where step 2 in step 1,
step 3 of destruction, finished the job.
Okay, So in my case,
all I've got is my string has
a pointer to dynamic storage and an integer.
The integer, there's nothing special to do.
The pointer, there'd be nothing special to
do once I got rid of that storage.
So all I have to do is get rid
of the dynamically allocated array
and that's the wrong way to do it.
So there's an annoying
little detail about C plus
plus when it comes to storage allocation and
deallocation that we have to deal with.
If you allocate something as a single object.
So maybe I have
some constructor parameters as well.
If I dynamically allocate one blah, object.
There it is with some constructor parameters.
If, if, if I want to
default construct the blob,
take this dynamically allocated,
I can leave off the, the parameters
Anna and leave off the parentheses if I like.
In any event, whichever way I do it,
this will create one blah,
objects and BP will point to it.
And when it's time for, to get rid of it,
you pass the pointer to that Blob
object, delete this way.
On the other hand, if
I declare an array of objects,
dynamically allocate an array of objects.
So let's say I dynamically allocate
an array of a 100 foo objects.
Now in order to have an array of
objects that have some type,
that type has to have a default constructor.
So, so foo, I'm assuming Foo has
a default constructor that
properly initializes a full object.
So that default constructor
will be called a 100
times one for each
of the four objects in the array.
So this will dynamically allocate
an array of a 100 items.
Nfp will point to element 0 of that array.
When it comes time to get rid of it,
you must use the array form of delete.
Let's delete an empty pair of
square brackets and the pointer.
Why?
There is a long reason for that.
But that's the role of the language.
If you allocate a single item, then with new,
then you delete it with
a single object form of nu,
which has no square brackets.
If you allocate an array of items with new,
when you delete it, you've gotta use
the delete square bracket form.
You pass appointed element 0, that array,
and two to delete square bracket,
and that'll,
that'll clean up the array properly.
Other restrictions are, if you
dynamically allocated an array.
The only pointer related to that array,
this legal to pass to delete
square brackets is a pointer
to element 0 of the array.
You can't, for example,
allocate a 100 element array,
get back a pointer to the beginning of
that array and decide,
you know, what, I want to get
rid of the last 20 elements.
So I will call delete
passing in a pointer to say FP plus 8.
So FP plus 80 would be
a pointer value that points two element,
element 80 of the array.
And you're hoping maybe
to get rid of elements
8399 to the array by
calling delete with that value.
Not allow undefined behavior.
The only pointer you can pass
to delete square bracket is,
is the same pointer value
that was given to you by now.
It could be in a different variable,
but it's a lot.
It's gotta be, it's gotta be
the address of element 0 of that array.
So, so there's, there's a limitation here.
Briefly.
The reason for having two different forms of
delete is basically an optimization,
a storage optimization decision by
Stroustrup in designing C plus plus, that,
if you have a pointer to a single object,
the only bookkeeping information you really,
the storage allocator really needs
is where is that object and how big is it?
So, so basically how big is that?
And obviously there's one
object if it's a class type,
I've got to call the destructor for
that class and get rid of the one object.
If you're dynamically allocating an array,
then the bookkeeping information
has to be a little more than that.
It can't just be how big is the array?
You know, I know, I know,
I know the type of object and,
and there's an end, and here's the array.
Because it needs to
know more than for a single object.
For single object, There's only one,
an array, there's a bunch.
And because there's a bunch,
that means the destructor
has to be called a bunch of times.
So there's more work to get rid of
an array because the destructor
is being called a certain number of times,
then there has to
be some bookkeeping information,
the records that there's
some number of times.
So the bookkeeping and information needed
for an array is more
than that for a single object.
And so, because there's like
two different ways or
two different things that we have to keep.
One is information for
a single object versus
information for an array.
You've gotta help the compiler a lot though
the runtime system along by indicating which,
which version is using.
There are some thoughts about well,
I started I went through the thought of well,
why not just have 11 form
for the booking information?
If there's only one form for
the bookkeeping information and there's
only one form of delete we need.
So why don't we just have
the storage allocator
treat a single object
as an array of one object.
So I'm saying it looks like the same thing.
Then everything is conceptually to the,
to the storage allocator, an array.
And so we can just
use the same algorithm there.
Well, the problem is if you have
a million single objects,
then since
the bookkeeping information for an array,
if we're treating each one of
them is an array of one object,
takes up more room than
a bookkeeping information for
just a single object in the normal sense,
then it's a lot of extra storage.
So blah, blah, blah.
You don't have to understand
that explanation at all.
I didn't give it very well.
The basic problem is
that the choice was either
simplify the language by
having one short one form of delete,
at the expense of taking up
more storage for lots and lots of
dynamically allocated single objects.
Or optimize the storage performance.
And just put the burden on the programmer to,
to distinguish between deleting
a single item or distinguishing an array.
He chose the latter.
One of the design goals of C plus plus
is for high-performance applications.
That also means not needlessly.
Using storage.
If you can come up with a way where,
where there's
a more efficient representation.
So the bird was passed on to us.
And so that means we have to keep track of
our pointers if we're dynamically
allocating something and
storing the result in a pointer
when it comes time to get rid of it,
you have to know how it was allocated.
Now in our case that simple
because we're always allocating an array.
So we know we're going
to be deleting an array.
And therefore, the correct implementation of
our destructor would be
to use the re-form the Delete.
Now that is correct.
Delete the stories that I'm texts 0.2,
which was allocated as an array.
So we use the array form of delete.
So now we have
our destructor correctly implemented
and that should solve
our resource management problems.
Australia.
Oh no, it does not.
There's still more.
We have the string class has some,
some serious problems that,
that we need to fix.
So I mean this part's fine.
They construct is find
the destructor is fine.
But there's more we need to
do to get correct behavior.
Let me just note that the steps of
destruction explain why we're okay.
Again, I had this employee type at some point
where let me go back.
We had this employee type and
this employee type it
back and see us 31 before I even saw classes.
We had this employee type that a
string, a double-ended end.
Now, if you create an employee,
that means each employee objects going to
have a data member of type string,
which probably has a pointer to
a dynamically allocated
array of characters for
the persons name is
strings generally will have
a pointer to the dynamically allocated array
of characters for the text.
At a double Internet.
We did not write a destructor for this type.
So if I have
an employee variable and later
on we leave the scope of that variable.
We leave the function where
that variable is declared.
The destructor for E gets called.
So we didn't write
a destructor for the employee types,
so the compiler writes one for
us that has an empty body.
Now why did we not have
a problem here with a memory leak?
Well, when the destructor
for this employee is called,
step one does nothing
because the compiler generate
the destructor has an empty body.
Step 2 says Destroy each data member.
So those of a built-in type, we do nothing.
So nothing happens regarding
the salary and the age.
But the name is
a string, that's a class type.
Name is a string.
String has a pointer to dynamic storage
0 should or we can have a memory leak?
No, because if the data members of
a class type that classes
destructor gets called,
destructor gets called.
So the string destructor will take
care of cleaning up this data member,
which is good and makes sense because,
why should we have to
know the details of how string is
implemented in order to
write an employee destructor.
If string chooses to dynamically
allocate storage as
part of this representation,
string is presumably
responsible for cleaning it up.
We, the designer or the employee
type should not have to worry about that.
And I don't care how strings
are implemented as long as
I know that strings a reasonable type,
the cleans up after itself.
When strings go away.
Then I'll just use strings
and it'll take care
that the dynamic storage form.
So that's why this, this employee type
worked out fine without a memory leak,
even though the string for the name
might have had pointer dynamic storage.
The strain destructor took care of
that and the rules of destruction,
make sure the string destructor got called.
Even though we didn't mentioned
a destructor for employee at all.
Okay, So we have a destructor for
our string class, which is good.
But as I said before,
we still have some resource
management problems here.
And we'll take a look at that next time.
So let me end the recording here.